<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The excellencie of the mysterie of Christ Iesus Declared in an exposition, or meditation vpon the 16. verse of the first epistle of Saint Paul vnto Timothie.</title>
            <author>Moffett, Peter, d. 1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07876</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18247</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114252</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849478</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849478</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14627</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07876)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14627)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1524:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The excellencie of the mysterie of Christ Iesus Declared in an exposition, or meditation vpon the 16. verse of the first epistle of Saint Paul vnto Timothie.</title>
                  <author>Moffett, Peter, d. 1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 66 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Orwin, for Raphe Iackson, and William Young,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Peter Moffet.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: P.M.</note>
                  <note>Decorative woodcut panel and ornamented factotum on A3r, first page of text, and K2v, final page ("A request to the Christian reader").</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14627:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14627:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Excellencie of the myſterie of Christ Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Declared in an expoſition, or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation vpon the 16. verſe of the firſt Epiſtle of Saint Paul vnto Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſ. 3.14. &amp;c.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For this cauſe I bow my knees vnto the Father of our Lord Ieſus Christ,</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <hi>15</hi> (Of whome is named the whole familie in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and in earth)</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <hi>16</hi> That he might graunt you according to the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his glorie, that yee may be ſtrengthened by his Spirit in the inner man,</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <hi>17</hi> That Christ may dwell in your hearts by faith, that yee being rooted and grounded in loue,</p>
               <p n="18">
                  <hi>18</hi> May be able to comprehend with all ſaints, what is the breadth, and length, and depth, and height:</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <hi>19</hi> And to knowe the loue of Christ, which paſſeth knowledge, that yee may be filled with all fulnes of God.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Orwin,</hi> for <hi>Raphe Iackson,</hi> and <hi>William Young.</hi> 1590.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14627:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14627:2"/>
            <head>To the two right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable ſisters, the Lady Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet, Counteſſe of Comber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and the Lady Anne, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of Warwicke; grace, mercie, and peace, be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied from God the father, and from the Lord Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndrie reaſons mooued me (most Honourable Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dames) both to publiſh this ſimple treatiſe, and to dedicate the ſame vnto your Ladyſhips. First of al, I wiſhed with <hi>Iob</hi> that <hi>my wordes
<pb facs="tcp:14627:3"/>were written,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 11.23.</note> 
               <hi>yea that they were imprinted in a booke;</hi> not, for that J longed to bring foorth ſome new diſcourſe into the world (which is pestered with infinit vnneceſſary pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets and treatiſes) but, for that I greatly deſired to ſpread that Doctrine farre and nere, wherein onely the fountaine of Saluation, and the flower of al ſounde conſolation conſisteth. Secondly, in theſe days (wherin is ſo much diſorder and diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions) I deemed it a moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie thing, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in open ſtreet (as it were) to point again vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Lambe of God, <hi>which
<pb facs="tcp:14627:3"/>taketh avvay the ſinnes of the VVorlde,</hi> that the ſimple may knowe what to ſtick vnto, &amp; where to begin the building of the ſpirituall houſe of their profeſſing the word, and ſeruing God aright. Thirdly, howſoeuer the fixing of ſuch a rude ſtock, as this homely diſcourſe is, in the ground of the Lords orchard, is indeed a work of no ſuch art or cunning, as whereby the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned may be increaſed in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, yet may it bee a meanes to ſtir vp ſome <hi>Paules</hi> or <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polloes,</hi> hereupon to ingraft more choice and excellent ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, and hereafter to ſet ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:14627:4"/>noble pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the tree of life, out of which most precious fruites may ſpring, to the benefit &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the Church, after that once the Lorde hath powred down his bleſſing on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Doctrine of <hi>the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> is ſuch a treaſure houſe of al good things and ſuch a root of true &amp; eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal happines, that whereſoeuer it is taught with wiſdome and with power, and receaued with reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, there glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry will aſſuredly dwell and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine. Yea there ſuch proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhal abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in citie &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, that <hi>grace &amp; faith ſhal meet
<pb facs="tcp:14627:4"/>together, righteouſnes and peace ſhall kiſſe each other,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 85.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>faith ſhall bud out of the earth, and righteouſnes ſhal looke dovvn from heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe were (Madames) the chiefeſt of thoſe reaſons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I was brought at last, after long withholding this my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation from the preſse, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit &amp; commit it thereunto, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit in mine owne opinion most vnworthy to come vnder it, but (in the iudgement of certaine ſpecial friends of mine, vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſight thereof hath bin im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted) conuenient, yea almost neceſſarie to be publiſhed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14627:5"/>
            <p>Now as concerning the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which made mee be ſo bold, as to dedicate this ſimple trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe vnto your Ladiſhips, they neither are in number fewer, than thoſe which induce me to let it come abroad, nor leſſe weighty in importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. First, for aſmuch as the Lorde hath cast vpon you all kindes of Honour in a manner, ſo that you ſeeme to ſtand amidſt the multitude of innumerable Chriſtians, or members of the Church among vs, as Paragons preferred in degree aboue the rest, &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſes of excellent and high ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; me thinketh, if any haue
<pb facs="tcp:14627:5"/>gathered an heape of ſweet &amp; pleaſant flowers out of the Scripture, for the vſe or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the profeſſors of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, that ſuch a garland is first to be proffered vnto your right honorable heads, &amp; muſt needs beſt fit, &amp; most ſeemely become your noble temples.</p>
            <p>Againe, ſeeing the fauour which you haue vouchſafed to beare and expreſſe toward mee hath been ſpeciall, J thought it my duety to repay ſome token of thankefulnes, firſt and especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally vnto your Ladiſhips: of whome what remembrance J haue, and toward whome what
<pb facs="tcp:14627:6"/>reuerence J beare. Finally, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom how great proſperity J wiſh, J knowe not by what meanes better to declare or te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie, than by dedicating a treatiſe vnto you, to giue you occaſion, both to knowe Christ Jeſus more fully, and to growe in him more firmely. Laſt of all, whereas, albeit your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states are full of the riches of Gods mercie, yet they are not ſo free from all aduerſitie, but that the Lorde of late hath exerciſed you with ſuch loſſes and croſses, as the Prophets ſpeake of, when they mention the tender mother bewailing
<pb facs="tcp:14627:6"/>hir first borne,<note place="margin">Zac. 12.10</note> and the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing yoke-fellowe girding hir ſelfe with ſackcloth for the huſband of her youth:<note place="margin">Ioel. 1.8.</note> it may bee that in <hi>the myſterie of Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> through the bleſſing of the Lorde, you ſhall finde ſome cordiall powder, which ſhall driue away your dolefull penſiueneſse in ſome parte: yea if you ſearch it throughlie, and make it your owne, it will vndoubtedlie giue <hi>you an Ornament in place of aſhes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 61.3, 4</note> 
               <hi>an oynteme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ioye in ſteed of mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, a Garment of praiſe in
<pb facs="tcp:14627:7"/>lievv of a broken ſpirit, that ye may be called the oakes of righteouſnes; that as the plants of Iehoua yee may glorie; that yee may builde the auncient vvaſt places, that ye may reſtore the old deſerts; that yee may renew the deſolate cities, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts of manie generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Accept then (Christian Madames) from thankefull heart, and reuerens hand, this little booke concerning the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of Christ Jeſus, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto your Ladiſhips,
<pb facs="tcp:14627:7"/>(not for that J ayme at anie preferment, or ſuch by-markes as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>) but onely for the cauſes before alleadged. Vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to protect it with your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, to pardon the defects and faults therein eſcaped: to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, to profit by thee mysterie there in deſcribed. Being now aſſured you will doe aboue that which is requested, J most hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly commend your Ladiſhips to the tuition and heauenly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of that good God, who hath ſo loued man in his Sonne Christ Jeſus, as to prepare for him, thoſe thinges which
<pb facs="tcp:14627:8"/>neither eye hath ſeene, nor eare hath heard, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be all<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.9.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> P.M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="exposition">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14627:8"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The excellencie of <hi>the myſterie of Chriſt</hi> Ieſus.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. Tim. 3. Chap. 16. ver.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And <hi>that</hi> mysterie of godlines is great <hi>by one aſſent,</hi> God <hi>hath been</hi> manifeſted in the fleſh, iustified in the ſpirite, ſeene by the Angels, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mong the nations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> in the world, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued vp in glorie.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He drift of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in this moſt precious ſentence, is to moue <hi>Timothie</hi> to behaue himſelfe verie religiouſlie and reuerentlie in the
<pb facs="tcp:14627:9"/>church of God, as may appeare both in the beginning of the verſe, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatlie before ſet downe in this chapter, and in the latter ende of the ſixt verſe of the next Chapter. One argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to this intent and purpoſe, hath bin already brought by him in the laſt wordes of the former ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; whereof this is the effect: ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the houſe or Church of God, whereof thou art a Miniſter, is not a ſinagogue of error, or a temple of types &amp; figures, but a proper pillar of truth: thou art as a pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſtian flock, to walke verie or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derlie, religiouſly and holylie, in all reſpects. Another reaſon tending vnto the ſelfe ſame end, is contained in this concluſion of the Chapter, whereof this is the ſumme: foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the Goſpell is a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent myſterie, it behooueth thee, a ſteward of ſuch ſecrets, to ſhew
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14627:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>all wiſdome and faithfulnes in the courſe of thy conuerſation, and in the execution of thy miniſterie.</p>
            <p>Now the excellencie of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is partly affirmed, and (as it were) inlarged by degrees, in the ſixe firſt words of this verſe, being theſe, <hi>And, that, mysteries, of godlines, is great,</hi> without doubt: partly proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and confirmed by ſixe ſeuerall reaſons in the latter ende of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, which reaſons are theſe; <hi>God hath been manifeſted in the fleſh; iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the ſpirit, ſeene by the Angels; preached among the nations; beleeued in the world; and receiued vp in glorie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt note here declaring the excellencie of Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is the particle or word, <hi>And:</hi> the which not onelie (as a knot) bindeth the former ſentence or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and this together: but as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the laſt word thereof,
<pb facs="tcp:14627:10"/>which was <hi>[trueth]</hi> declareth, that the maine veritie, which the houſe of God, or the Chriſtian Church, chiefelie and continuallie vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth; is the myſterie of godlines, or faith in Chriſt Ieſus. It was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie needefull for <hi>Paul</hi> to expound himſelfe after this manner, and to inſinuate this matter vnto <hi>Timothie,</hi> and in him to all the faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and beleeuers of the Goſpell. For elſe, they taking through error their markes amiſle, and thinking the holding of any truth, a ſufficient proofe or note of this true Church, might conclude the Iewiſh ſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue or ſome ſuch like aſſemblie, to bee the houſe of GOD; becauſe therin ſome truth is kept &amp; found: or againe, they running into another extremitie, might raſhly condemne ſome beleeuing and chriſtian chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, (as the Church at <hi>Corinth</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14627:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>cauſe euen they ſometimes erre or diſſent about ſome points of trueth, which yet are of leſſe importance.</p>
            <p>To the end therefore that all the faithfull may in all times and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and among all perſons, knowe which is the Lords holy campe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort thereto, and remaine therein; the Apoſtle ſheweth here, that it may alwaies bee diſcerned by this banner or enſigne of the Myſterie of the Goſpell. Thoſe congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then are vndoubtedly the true Churches of God, which firmelie hold the articles of faith, and ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge Chriſt Ieſus to bee the Sonne of God, and the onelie foundation of ſaluation: howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer otherwiſe peraduenture they be farre from ſpotles perfection.<note place="margin">Reuel. 1.2, 3. c.</note> Had not the Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> much droſſe, and many cracks? Did not the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> ſomewhat
<pb facs="tcp:14627:11"/>coole and quench the burning lamp of hir former loue? Were there not ſundry members of the church at <hi>Sardis,</hi> which had names of life on them, but wounds of death in them? How came it to paſſe that in the Chriſtian aſſembly at <hi>Perga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> there were ſuch as held the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of <hi>Balaam,</hi> if that the eye ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of did not winke, or was not faſt a ſleepe? And where was the rodde or ſhepheards crooke of the paſtor of the Congregation at <hi>Thyatyra:</hi> when <hi>Iezabel</hi> was ſuffered to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the Lord? How luke-warme were euen the beſt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in all <hi>Laodicea,</hi> when our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our cried out thus againſt the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of them, <hi>would to God thou wert either hot or colde?</hi> Theſe faultes were found in all theſe Churches: yea in the meſſengers ſent vnto them, and therefore in the members
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14627:11"/>of them. And yet what are theſe Churches in his account, who wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the middeſt of them, but gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den candleſticks? What names dooth the giue to the meſſengers of theſe congregations, but <hi>Starres:</hi> ſo called by him in regarde of their places, and the ſhining of thoſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which were ſomewhat dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but not quite quenched? Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallie what promiſes maketh he, or what ſpeeches vſeth he to the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of thoſe beleeuing aſſemblies? but that (vpon condition, that they repented and continued in well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) they ſhould eate of the tree of life, feede on the hidden manna, rule ouer the Nations, and ſtand as pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars in the Temple of GOD for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer?</p>
            <p>Hee dooth not aduiſe them to forſake their mutuall fellowſhip, he dooth not denie them to bee mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb facs="tcp:14627:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>of his bodie, becauſe they did not rent themſelues from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of their Congregations ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed and infected, he willeth them not to diſclaime the eyes which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected them no better, he affirmeth not, that their teachers are none of his Miniſters, their Sacraments no Sacraments vnto him, becauſe his order was not obſerued or execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and becauſe certaine <hi>Balaams</hi> and <hi>Iezabels</hi> were mingled in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly with his ſeruants. Yea on the contrarie ſide; notwithſtanding all theſe wants, neglects, diſorders, offences and blemiſhes whatſoeuer, he alloweth and accepteth the good things which were in any profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and calleth theſe aſſemblies golden candleſticks (as before hath been ſhewed) concluding that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hath an eare, is to heare what the ſpirit ſpeaketh vnto the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14627:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>Churches, ſo that look what iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment our ſauiour Chriſt Ieſus gaue touching the Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> the ſame are all Chriſtians to haue of the Churches of <hi>Europe,</hi> not one of which is without ſome ſpot or wrinckle. Wherefore let euery one take heede how hee leaueth our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies and Chriſtian congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt going about to be more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> than the rule, more bright than the ſunne, more right handed than the right hand it ſelfe, to conclude, more perfect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the word of God: whileſt he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>efull and endeuoreth to auoide one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremetie, through ignorance or blinde zeale hee runne into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Now if thoſe reuolters (which ſo wander on the right hand, as that they condemne our Chriſtian Congregations which receiue and
<pb facs="tcp:14627:13"/>acknowledge the great myſterie of Chriſt Ieſus here ſpoken of) cannot be excuſed, neither are to be iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in regarde of their error, or raſh ſeparation: notwithſtanding that they neither denie any of the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of faith, nor fall downe before ſtockes or ſtones? what is to be ſaid of thoſe recuſants on the contrarie ſide, and as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he left hand which art ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to Chriſt Ieſus, that Antichriſt is vnto them all in all, and that they embrace the myſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> of all iniquitie and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> euen the abominable and execrable hereſie of poperie?</p>
            <p>Theſe Enemies of the grace of GOD, affirme and vaunt that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the houſe of God, and the pillar of trueth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as rather it is indeede a denne of theeues, and a ſea of al impietie and diueliſh apoſtacie or backſliding
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14627:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>from the faith. But as for the church of <hi>England,</hi> it pleaſeth them not, and therefore they either come not at all to our aſſemblies (becauſe indeed they haue ſworne obedience to the ſinagogue of Antichriſt) or if anie reſort now &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto our church, it is for that the Machiuell in their head, hath for the time gotten the vpper hand of the Pope in their bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. They ſay they beleeue in Chriſt, yea and in the holy Trinity: but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they lay another foundation of ſaluation, beſides the ſonne of God, to wit, the abominable idoll of the maſſe, they cannot be the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of GOD, yea they muſt needes be moſt vile idolaters. They talke much of good workes, but ſeeing thereby they profeſſe to be ſaued, as for the ſame deſeruing the fauour of God, and eternall life; the very Publicans and ſinners, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:14627:14"/>and confeſsing their ſinnes, ſhal be taken vp into heauen, when they with all their merits ſhall be caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hel. They worſhip a paltrie pope, and fall downe daily before grauen images and idols; in the meane ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they make no conſcience to riſe vp in armes againſt Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to hatch the egges of <hi>Aſps</hi> againſt Gods people. They call the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues Catholiques, as if forſooth they were of the company of true beleeuers, or the right worſhippers of God, but in trueth they are a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of vipers, which from time to time haue perſecuted, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, and put to death the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God, and daily thirſt after, &amp; long to ſuck their bloud. It is no maruell then if the fruites of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, hate the aſſemblies of Chriſt Ieſus or refuſe to ioyne with vs in the word and the Sacraments, but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14627:14"/>rather it is to bee wondered at, that the worſhippers of the true God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt not with a perfect hatred, ſuch malitious idolaters as thoſe Papiſts are, which wiſh for a day, who haue attempted ſo many treaſons, and beare a falſe heart againſt their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue countrey, beſides a bloudy rage againſt the Religion.</p>
            <p>Now as there are ſuch recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants, as (vtterly refuſing to come to the aſſemblies, wherein the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of godlineſſe is acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and beleeued) do dangerouſly keepe out the Arke and houſe of God, marked with the bloud of the Lambe Chriſt Ieſus; ſo there are a great number of prophane profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, who imagine themſelues to be in the boſome of the Church, when they are indeede in the very bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the wrath of God, and who very ſeldome and ſparingly reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:14627:15"/>vnto the preaching of the word and the Sacraments amongſt vs, make as it were an open profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of vngodlines and impietie.</p>
            <p>Whoſe heart would not rue to thinke vppon, or beholde this kinde of people, in whom raigneth an vntolerable neglect &amp; contempt of holy things? Theſe on the Saba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth in the forenoone, peraduenture will be at Church, but in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone at the alehouſe. Once in a tweluemonth (as at <hi>Eaſter</hi>) they wil come to the Communion, but after the receauing of it, it is their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to runne into all exceſſe of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot, gadding and madding after their pleaſures and vanities. They ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge Baptiſme to be a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and bring their Children to Church to bee Baptized, but when the Miniſter commeth to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter it to any infant, they depart from
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14627:15"/>the aſſembly, no more accounting of this ſacred ſeale of the new coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, than as of ſome common or prophane waſhing. They wil not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to pray ſome times, but they wil continually ſweare and blaſpheme. They deny not altogether to heare Sermons or preaching of the word, but they like better of gaming, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, carding, dancing, fenſing, drinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and feaſting than of that. They doo not condemne the Goſpell, nor the exerciſes of Religion, as reading the Word, ſinging, praier or ſuch like. But their onelie life is to be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied rather, in goſsiping, in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and reſorting vnto playes and places of all diſorder. Yet thoſe are in their owne eyes, and alſo in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon account of the moſt, the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie or beſt profeſſors of the word, whoſe waies yet are ſo impious, &amp; whoſe prophanenes ſo appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. But
<pb facs="tcp:14627:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>let them take heede,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.24.</note> (ſo to conclude this point) how they tread the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of GOD vnder foote, and doo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt the bloud of the couenant common, whereby they are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, or be iniurious to the ſpirite of grace: for we know him that hath ſaide, <hi>Venegeance is mine, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paie it ſaieth the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond word here to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered is the Article, <hi>That,</hi> ſhewing in this place, that the myſterie ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, hath in it ſome ſpeciall dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,<note place="margin">Iohn. 1.29.</note> and excellencie. <hi>Iohn</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt pointing to our Sauiour, vſed the ſame worde, or Article to the ſame effect, when he ſaide. <hi>Behold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> That Lambe;</hi> the ſame Euangeliſt <hi>Iohn</hi> alſo, going about to put a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene the Meſsias, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Iohn. 1.8.</note> calleth Chriſt <hi>that light.</hi> As therefore the ſun comming foorth like a bridegroom out of his cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14627:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhineth more clearely than al the Starres in the firmament beſide: ſo euen among the other doctrines of the Scripture, this excelleth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the glory of the Heauenly Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome Chriſt Ieſus is preſented vnto our view. Furthermore as a pearle far ſurpaſſeth pibble ſtones: ſo this trueth all the precepts of phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, all the ſciences and artes ſet downe in bookes, and ſtudied by men. Seeing then this myſterie is ſo peerles a pearle, what wiſe chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian marchant is there, who would not ſell his pleaſures, profits, yea life and all to buie it? Againe who is there ſo depriued of vnderſtanding, who once hauing gotten ſome ſight of it, or right in it, would ſell ſuch a iewell for ſinne, for honour, for gaine, or for the whole world? The counſaile then of <hi>Salomon</hi> touching this matter is alway to bee remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred
<pb facs="tcp:14627:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>by euery Chriſtian,<note place="margin">Pro. 23.23.</note> 
               <hi>Buie the trueth, but ſell it not, euen wiſdome, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and vnderſtanding.</hi> Now the trueth and wiſdome, which the wiſe King meaneth, is that myſtery here ſpoken of, which Philoſophie ſeeketh, but diuinitie findeth, and godlines poſſeſſeth.</p>
            <p>Againe, hereupon it followeth, that there is a certaine dignitie and preheminence of the diſpenſers of the myſteries of the Goſpell, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen aboue the miniſters of the law, inaſmuch as the myſterie of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie, hath in it ſuch a ſpecial ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie, and prerogatiue. For as our Apoſtle reaſoneth elſewhere,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.9.</note> if the miniſtery of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were glorious: much more doth the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie of righteouſnes, exceede in glorie. Our Sauiour alſo affirmeth in the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Luc. 7.28.</note> not onely that <hi>Iohn</hi> was more then a Prophet, but that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14627:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>he which is leaſt in the Kingdome of Heauen is greater than he. For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as a peece of an oken boord, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit little worth as of it ſelfe, yet when it hath in the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ure of the Prince moſt flouriſhingly and liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie painted, is more worth, &amp; more to be eſteemed for that cauſe; than a boord of Cedar, which wanteth the ſame image, or hath it but darkely and rudely purtrayed and drawne out: ſo the miniſtery of the Goſpell; repreſenting our Heauenly Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Chriſt Ieſus moſt plainelie and clerely, is therefore to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and in deede more honorable, than the Miniſterie of the Lawe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore their condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſleepeth not, who in theſe daies are ſo farre of from eſteeming or reuerencing the meſſengers of the word, that they reiect them as the doung and ofſcouring of the
<pb facs="tcp:14627:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>earth. For if a mortall Prince can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide, that his Ambaſſadours ſhould be deſpiſed or abuſed: much more wil the Lord reuenge the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch is ſhewed againſt thoſe, whome hee ſendeth on his meſſage, yea on this glorious and moſt famous ambaſſage of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. For he hath ſaide in his word, <hi>Touch not mine annoynted, and doo my Prophets no harme.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>Hee that toucheth you, toucheth the apple of mine eye. He that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third point in this commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Goſpell by vs to bee obſerued, is, that it is a <hi>(myſterie).</hi> The which word in the Greeke tongue dooth ſignifie a ſecret or an hidden matter: it is alſo vſually ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, to note out thoſe precepts &amp; things, which are ſacred, and chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to bee regarded. But albeit the Goſpell is here termed a <hi>mysterie:</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:14627:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>yet the apoſtles meaning is not, that it is ſuch a ſecret, as ought not to be communicated to the common multitude. For the Lord enioining his Diſciples to teach all Nations, and to preach the Goſpell vnto eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry creature,<note place="margin">Mar. 16.15</note> whether Male or Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, learned or vnlearned, young or old, in them willeth and warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all his Miniſters, to impart this Doctrine to all ſortes of people.</p>
            <p>Neither is the Doctrine of the new Teſtament in any ſuch ſorte here tearmed a <hi>myſterie,</hi> as if it were after a more dark manner ſet down &amp; deliuered vnto vs, than the book of the Law, or the olde couenant. For <hi>in former ages</hi> (ſaieth this our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle elſewhere) <hi>this ſecret was not ſo manifeſted vnto the ſonnes of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>as now it hath been reuealed to the ſaintes and Prophets by the ſpirit.</hi> For as one ſaith verie well, the old Teſtament is the
<pb facs="tcp:14627:19"/>new incloſed in obſcuritie, and the new is the old vnfolded in the light.</p>
            <p>Theſe two couenants differ in circumſtance and manner, but they are the ſame, and agree in ſubſtance and effect. But firſt the power of the Goſpell is a <hi>myſterie</hi> to all the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, whoſe eyes the GOD of this World hath ſo blinded, that they cannot ſee the trueth vnto Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, neither doo they ſoundlie and continually feele, that they are in Gods fouour: yea becauſe Chriſt Ieſus the root of mortification, and ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not planted in them, they are vnable and vnfit to euerie good worke.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Tit. 1.16.</note> the very matter of the Goſpell it ſelfe is myſticall and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret: the beginnings or firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples whereof, as the naturall man by any light within him,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.14</note> or ſight of the creatures without him cannot
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14627:19"/>perceiue: ſo neither can the ſpiritual man (although taught by the word, and lightned by grace) reache or ſound the full deapth or bottome. For howſoeuer euery true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an borne againe by the ſpirite, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſeeth ſo much of this myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as is ſufficient for his ſaluation: yet none hath attained, or can come to the perfect vnderſtanding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. There is in deede no ſkill or trade, although neuer ſo hard, or full of curious points, which ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of pregnant wittes, or very quick conceites, are not able ſoone to learne, or at leaſt by much labour and endeuour ſo to attaine, that at laſt they come to the perfection thereof, and excell therein. But as concerning the ſauing and bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe knowledge of Chriſt Ieſus, (which is in deede the onlie arte or peece of cunning in the world,) it
<pb facs="tcp:14627:20"/>ſo farre paſſeth the reach, not onely of men, but of Angels, that no crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is able fully to conceiue it, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dooth any comprehend it. If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mortal wight euer ſaw the depth of this ſecret, was it any other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide this our <hi>Paul,</hi> who being taken vp into the third Heauens, heard words, which cannot be vttered, &amp; contrary to his cuſtome magnifieth his knowledge in this myſterie? No other out of doubt, than the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Paradiſe, the ſchoolefellowe of the Angels, the Preacher of the Gentiles: finallie, hee who wiſhed himſelfe accurſed for his countrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men the Iewes. Neuertheleſſe euen this great Apoſtle affirmeth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,<note place="margin">1. Co. 13.11</note> that hee knoweth but in part; and of vs, that wee ſee but as in a glaſſe darkelie. As for the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels, why dooth the Apoſtle <hi>Peeter</hi> ſay,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.22</note> that euen they deſire
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14627:20"/>throughly to view the <hi>myſterie</hi> here ſpoken of, if they vnderſtand it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectlie and exactly?</p>
            <p>And now then, ſeeing this ſecret is hidden from the reprobate, ſeeing as it is the power of God vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation to the elect, ſo euen to them it is as a treaſure hid (in a great part) in the ground; ſeeing the Angels prie into the riches of Gods wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome herein with great delight: concerneth it not euery Chriſtian, to exerciſe himſelfe verie diligently in the knowledge, feeling and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of this myſterie? Certainelie whoſoeuer ſhall not know God, as he is made knowne in Ieſus Chriſt, as aliens or ſtrangers from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſhal at the day of iudgement feele the fire of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance fal vpon them.<note place="margin">2. The 1.8.</note> Againe, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hauing knowne this trueth in ſome meaſure, ſhall careleſlie,
<pb facs="tcp:14627:21"/>contemptuouſly, willingly, wholy finally fall from all knowledge, fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, working and practiſe of it,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.4.</note> can no more bee renued to repentance by any good meanes tending there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, than any fruite which hath fallen from the tree can ſo be ſet on the bough againe, as that it ſhall grow theron, or tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a dead man can be recouered to life by Phiſick, or an earthen veſſell broken to peeces or to powder, bee ioyned together firmelie by the potters skill. For, when the whole lampe of good workes ſhall quite bee quenched, when all the drops of faith ſhall bee caſt or ſpurted out, when ſhipwrack ſhall be made of the maine ſtocke of Gods gracious ſpirite, when the nouriſhing foode of the word ſhall bee loathed and reiected, when the ſtrength of hope, concerning a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eſtate at the reſurrection, ſhall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14627:21"/>vtterly be conſumed; what repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance can there be: the life whereof is faith; the ſtrength whereof is hope, the food wherof is the word, the fountaine whereof is the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, the fruites whereof are good workes?</p>
            <p>Nay, in that theſe prophane backſliders, willinglie puſh from them all godlines and the Goſpell, what doo they herein, but crucifie the ſonne of God, vnto themſelues, as if he were a vile perſon, or an c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill dooer, piercing him through, albeit not with nayles, yet with moſt grieuous and innumerable ſinnes: yea making a gazing or moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſtock of him, albeit not by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vinegar to his noſtrels, or thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting his heart through with a ſpeare, yet by vexing his ſpirit, and not eſteeming or truſting in his bloud, as if it had no price or vertue
<pb facs="tcp:14627:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>in it, but were like vnto the bloud of beaſts or of mortall men.</p>
            <p>This is the fearefull eſtate of back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliders from the Goſpell, not of thoſe, in whome many good things are, yea or one ſparke of faith or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to Gods lawes, is founde and abiding. So wretched is the condition of thoſe, who only haue the braunches of the ſpirit, not of thoſe, who haue in them the roote of this myſterie, Chriſt Ieſus. For as concerning the right Chriſtians, they are not lampes quicklie quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched for want of oyle, but lightes alway ſhining in good works;<note place="margin">Phil. 2.15.</note> they are not like cookes or taſters, which let not their meates or drinkes goe downe, but ſuch which keep faith in a good conſcience, ſo that it tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth into their ſpirituall nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.9</note> they are not partners of the holy ſpirit for a yeare or two; nor
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14627:22"/>bankrupt Marchants, which breake vpon a ſodaine; but ſuch as abound dayly more and more,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.5. 1. Tim. 6.18</note> and waxe wealthie in ſpiritual giftes: they are not day labourers or hired ſeruants which for a ſhort time onely ſit vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Lords roofe, or eate at his table; but as Children of adoption, they feede dayly on the word, and remaine in the houſe of God for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer:<note place="margin">Pſal 23.5.6.</note> they are not ſuch diſeaſed or bedred perſons, who faint with weaknes, &amp; die for want of breath: but being ſtrengthened by hope in the inner man,<note place="margin">Ephe. 3.16.</note> they more than con quer like valiant Captaines, getting the victorie ouer ſinne, ſatan, and all temptations.<note place="margin">Rom. 8 37.</note> Now this happie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate they attaine vnto by the ſeeing of the height, depth, length, breadth, and that knowledge of the loue of Chriſt, which ſurpaſſeth all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.<note place="margin">Ephe. 3.18.</note>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14627:23"/>
            <p>Wherefore,<note place="margin">I am. 1.25.</note> whoſoeuer ſhall looke into this glaſſe of the Goſpel, ſo reuerently, earneſtly and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallie, that he ſhall be tranſformed into the image of Chriſt,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3 18</note> from glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to glorie, as by the ſpirite of the Lord: he ſhall be by ſo much farre of from the miſerie of reuolters, by how much hee profiteth in this myſterie,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.8.</note> and by ſo much nearer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly happines, by how much more carefully and happilie, he wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in this way leading thereunto. Wherefore alſo euery one ought to be,<note place="margin">Heb. 5.11.12, 13, 14. 15.</note> not a rude or young ſchollet, but well learned in this ſecret, not a childe or babe, but a ſtrong and olde man in the myſterie of Chriſt, both as concerning the knowledge, fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and practiſe thereof.</p>
            <p>In the fourth place it is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, that Chriſtian Religion is not onely here called a ſecret, but a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14627:23"/>
               <hi>myſterie of godlines,</hi> or of the right worſhip of God. The Miniſterie of the leuiticall Prieſthoode, and the whole ſeruice of God vſed by the Iewiſh people, was a patterne of godlines. For firſt, there was among the Iſraelites &amp; ouer them, an high Prieſt,<note place="margin">Exod. 29.7.</note> conſecrated with ſundrie ſolemne ceremonies, as namely, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynting of him with oyle,<note place="margin">Leuit. 8.23</note> putting the bloud of the Sacrifice on the lap of his right eare, &amp; vpon the thumb of his right hand, &amp; vpon the great toe of his right foote, to conclude, clothing him with moſt pretious and glorious garments.<note place="margin">Exod. 29.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Now his office was,<note place="margin">Heb 9.7.</note> once a yeare to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the moſt holy place, and to offer vp giftes &amp; ſacrifice vnto the Lord,<note place="margin">Heb. 8.3. Leuit. 24.3 1. Sa. 2.28.</note> as alſo to dreſſe the lampes, and to ſet them before the Lorde, and to burne incenſe before him, and to weare before him an Ephod.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14627:24"/>
            <p>Secondly, there were inferiour Prieſts of the ſonnes of <hi>Aaron</hi> alſo, whoſe ſeruice was,<note place="margin">Num. 4.16</note> to teach, to pray, to ſacrifice continually, to offer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, to preſerue the oyle,<note place="margin">Mat. 2.7.</note> to looke vnto the holy veſſels, and to doo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch workes. Thirdly, the reſt of the Leuites, which deſcended not from <hi>Aaron,</hi> but from <hi>Greſhom</hi> and <hi>Merari,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cron. 1.13</note> were appointed to ſundrie offices: ſome to play vpon inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of muſick in the temple, ſome to ſing,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.17.11.27.</note> ſome to keepe the doores, ſome to other ſeruices. Laſt of all the Iewiſh people being all, firſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, brought their beaſtes to ſacrifice, and their other giftes to offer, receiued the Paſſcouer, and walked in thoſe ordinances and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, which the Lord had preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed vnto them.</p>
            <p>All theſe were worſhippers not of idols but of the true God,<note place="margin">Luk. 1.6.</note> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14627:24"/>and performing in their ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, not the inuentions of men, but the preſcript and ordinances of the liuing Lord. Wherefore this pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie of the Iewes, (I ſay) was a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of godlines; but the ſubſtance of it is onely to be found in the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and in the Chriſtian Church. For firſt of all, ouer the Chriſtian aſſembly of the faithful,<note place="margin">Heb 7.26.</note> there is not a ſinful, but an holy and perfect high Prieſt, who hauing been anoynted with the oyle of gladnes aboue his fellowes,<note place="margin">Luk. 24 39</note> and conſecrated by afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and bloud in his hands and feete, hath not onely offered praiers and teares to God,<note place="margin">Heb 5.7.</note> but ſacrificed his owne ſoule and body: which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing rightly done in all reſpects, now he maketh interceſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſuch ſort to his father,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.34.</note> that he cannot but grant to euery one of the faithfull, whatſoeuer is needefull for him.
<pb facs="tcp:14627:25"/>Moreouer al Chriſtians by him are made (as it were) princely prieſts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.5.</note> leuites to laud him, and Iewes in the ſpirit to worſhip him,<note place="margin">Ephe. 5.19.</note> ſo that euery belecuer practiſeth godlines in a myſtery,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.29.</note> and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the right ſeruice of God in an excellent manner.<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> Dooth not the Chriſtian, of what calling ſoeuer, as a Prieſt ſpirituall, not onely offer vp his heart, but his whole bodie, as an holy, liuelie and acceptable ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to God? Approacheth he not by faith vnto the throne of grace? Dooth not he pray for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and others with grones, which cannot be expreſſed?<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26</note> Dooth he not take heed,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.19</note> that hee quench not the Spirit? Singeth he not Pſalmes and hymnes with ſpirituall ſongs in his heart vnto the Lord?<note place="margin">Col. 3.16.</note> Laboureth hee not to keepe the doores of his lippes from corrupt ſpeach?<note place="margin">Pſal. 141.3.</note> Is not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14627:25"/>he circumciſed inwardly, or dooth not the Spirite write the lawes of GOD in his heart?<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.3.</note> Certainely let Chriſt Ieſus once dwel in the heart of any by faith, and he will foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with make that man to walk in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming ſincerely (though not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly) euevey one of the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of the Law.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.10 Jam. 2.11.12.</note> For firſt of all, the Chriſtian cannot but know the father,<note place="margin">Joh. 14.9.</note> whoſe ſonne dwelleth in him: neither can he but truſt in his Sauiour, who ſhed his bloud for him. As for the holy ſpirit,<note place="margin">Rom 8.32. Pſal. 16.7. and 116.1.</note> which hath beſtowed the riches of his grace on him, he muſt of neceſsitie both loue and reuerence his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and ſo conſequently acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, feare, loue,<note place="margin">Iam. 4.12</note> and truſt in one true GOD in three perſons. Now ſeeing the Chriſtian hath but one Maſter, Prophet or lawgiuer, hee will not for all the goods in the
<pb facs="tcp:14627:26"/>world once bow the knee to Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, neither wil he receiue any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions or traditions of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.11</note> which apparantlie are contrarie to the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, ſeeing that prince go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneth him, whoſe kingdome can not be ſhaken,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> he hath a power of ſeruing God with ſhamefaſtnes, and warines, whereby it commeth to paſſe, that he baniſheth othes and blaſphemies out of his mouth, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taketh he the grace of God in vaine: but when he vſeth the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, beholdeth the creatures, or heareth the word,<note place="margin">1. Th. 2.13.</note> ſuffereth all theſe as wholeſome medicines to haue in him due operations. Againe, in as much as his heauenly captaine hath brought him into the Lords reſt, he is ſo farre off from prophaning the Sabaoth day, by abſenting himſelfe from the publique exerciſes of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14627:26"/>or by working, or loytering,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.8, 9, 10.</note> that euery day is to him as a ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Sabaoth, inwardly exerciſing himſelfe from time to time, in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and practiſing the will of God, labouring not to walke in his owne way,<note place="margin">Eſay. 58.13</note> nor to ſpeake a vaine word. To conclude, he maketh conſcience of deſpiſing any ſuperiors whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,<note place="margin">Col. 3.18. &amp;c.</note> of not gouerning his inferiors aright, of being angrie, quarrelling,<note place="margin">Mat 5.22 &amp;c.</note> and fighting, of being intemperate, or vnchaſt in geſtures, ſpeeches, diet and apparell; of couetouſnes, ſloth, vnthriftines and deceipt, of ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, lying, teuiling, taunting, yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of deſiring, wiſhing, or thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king euill; becauſe not onely a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of mortification,<note place="margin">Col. 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> but a power &amp; ſtrength of ſanctification, preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and guideth his ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. And is not this then the beſt and the chiefeſt godlines in deede, yea
<pb facs="tcp:14627:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>is not this the onely right and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent manner of ſeruing of God?<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now hereby it appeareth that poperie is but a counterfaite of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and not ſo much as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> patterne thereof, as was the Iewiſh policie or order of ſeruing God. That here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie (as the fooliſh woman ſpoken of in the Prouerbes) is very full of words and motions,<note place="margin">Pro. 9.13.</note> with queſtions about the true worſhip of GOD, which it knoweth not. Oh how zealous are the maſſemo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers about their vnbloudy ſacrifice, which hath coſt ſo much bloud? They ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a ſacrifice; it is wel: and ſacrificing prieſts, ſuch are al Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: and an altar, it is true, wee haue a ſacred ſanctuarie Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. But the bread forſooth muſt be turned into the body of Chriſt, and his body muſt be offered vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, a ſhaueling muſt be the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14627:27"/>ſuch a one, who (as if he were a worker of feates) can turne about in a circle, and occupie his fingers about making croſſes, caſt his armes all abroad, lift them vp and pul them downe againe, mumble vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and by and by ſpeake vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with a loude voyce; whiſper a while to the bread, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> break out into a ſhrill note or ſong</p>
            <p>But to let ſuch popiſh and apiſh toyes paſſe, true godlines conſiſteth not (as hath been ſhewed) either in humane traditions, or wil worſhip, or in bodily exerciſes,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> as abſtaining from meates, drinkes, ſleepe, or ſuch humbling of the body, (as it is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the mortifying of the ſoule,)<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.5</note> nor in a bare profeſsion of the trueth, but in faith in Ieſus Chriſt, and obedience to his lawes, both inwardlie and outwardly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14627:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The fift poynt to be conſidered by vs in this commendation of the Goſpell is, that the myſterie of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines is <hi>great, excellent, or notable.</hi> It is firſt of all very great in fame, and renowme, according as the Prophet ſheweth; when going about to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of the myſtery of the incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the ſufferings and the glorify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſonne of God, hee crieth out twice in one Pſalme. <hi>O Lorde how excellent is thy name throughout the world!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 8. 1. Cor. 1.24</note> But againe, the Goſpel is as great in fruite, as it is in fame, in regarde whereof it is truely called <hi>the Power of God vnto ſaluation, the wiſdome of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 16. Ioh. 6.68.</note> finallie, <hi>the word of life.</hi> For this is eternall life to know the true God, and him, whome he hath ſent Ieſus Chrſt. The magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence of this myſterie further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more appeareth; in the figures and types of the Lawe, as the tabernacle,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14627:28"/>the temple, the red ſea, the cloude, the manna, and the redemption of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Aegipt.</hi> For if the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures were ſo excellent, what is the body? If ſuch glorious things are ſpoken in the ſcripture of the types, what may be thought of the trueth it ſelfe? To be briefe, the ſpouſe in the diuine booke of the ſong of ſongs, playing (if I may ſo ſpeake) the very blab, and blazing to al men the ſecrets of hir loue,<note place="margin">The Song of Songs. 5.10, 11.</note> telling that Chriſt Ieſus is white and ruddie, the chiefe among ten thouſand, that his head is as fine golde, his lockes curled and black as a Rauen; decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red plainely, and ſufficiently wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, that this myſterie concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Chriſt and his Church, is great indeed. It is, as hath been ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, very great in fame (for the <hi>ſound of it hath gone throughout the world</hi>) great alſo in fruit,<note place="margin">Ro. 16.18.</note> 
               <hi>(For it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb facs="tcp:14627:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>wiſe vnto ſaluation)</hi> moreouer great in quality (for hereof the types of the law are euen but ſhadowes):<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.15</note> but laſt of all it is furthermore ſo great in quantity,<note place="margin">Col. 2.17.</note> that the moſt skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Geometrician in the World, is not able to take the meaſure of it by any meanes, for that is altogether infinit.<note place="margin">Ephe. 3 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Prophet ſpeaking of this matter in the Pſalme and directing his ſpeech vnto the Lorde, ſayeth thus. <hi>Thy mercie O Lord reacheth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heauens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>and thy trueth vnto the cloudes, thy righteouſnes is like vnto the mountaines, thy iudgements are like a great deepe, O Lord thou ſaueſt both man and beaſt.</hi> In deede our Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Fpheſians,</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that he prayed for them vnto the Lord, that they might bee able to comprehend with all the ſaints, that height, length, breadth and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14627:29"/>depth, which reacheth to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, to the ſeas, to the ends of the earth, and the furtheſt partes of the World. But he meaneth not in this his ſupplication, to ſhew, that any is able to attaine vnto the perfection of this knowledge, which paſſeth all knowledge, but onely hee wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth, that the <hi>Epheſians</hi> may haue an abilitie or gift from aboue, to ſee theſe meaſures in an acceptable meaſure for their comfort and the fortifying of their faith. For ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of himſelfe in his epiſtle to the <hi>Philippians</hi> (who ſaw no doubt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this myſterie, as farre as any mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man) hee profeſſeth that he had not yet attained this knowledge, neither was perfited,<note place="margin">Phil 3.12.</note> but that he did follow after the ſame to apprehend it. The wiſe Agur alſo intreating of this matter, not onely confeſſeth that hee had not learned this wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb facs="tcp:14627:30"/>or knowledge of holie things: but demaundeth the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Who hath aſcended into Heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro 30.1.2 &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>and deſcended thence? Who can gather the winde in his fist? Who can binde the Waters in his garment? Who can eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the borders of the earth? What is the name of ſuch a one? and what is his ſonnes name?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the which words (as it ſeemeth) that great clarke or Prophet inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to ſhew, not onely that none knoweth the father, but the ſonne, and he to whom the ſonne will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale him, but that none perfectlie knoweth either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both, as may appeare in that he ſaieth, there is not any, which can meaſure or rule theſe great creatures or elements, namely the earth, the waters, and the ayre, &amp; in that he asketh what the name of the Father and of the Sonne is?</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:14627:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Seeing now the miſtery of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is ſo great, yea in alreſpects ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, it behoueth the diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, with great care &amp; conſcience to execute that holy miniſtery, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto they are ſet apart. For how els ſhall they bee able to anſwer in any reſpect vnto that honorable functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whereunto they are called? Yea how can they but ſtaine and pollute the peerleſſe pearle committed to their truſt, to keepe and carrie? It behooueth them therefore, firſt of all, as wiſe builders,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.10</note> chiefelie and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially to lay the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt Ieſus, and to declare vnto their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the articles of faith, which are the maine and principall pillers (as it were) of the ſpirituall building. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, as the foundation is noble, ſo vpon the ſame, not the wood, hay, or ſtraw of Rhetoricall, Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophicall, or humaine skill or elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,
<pb facs="tcp:14627:31"/>but the golde, ſiluer and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtones, of a ſimple, graue, and ſpirituall maner of teaching, is to be laid. Thirdly, the affection &amp; iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the interpreter of the word ought alwaies ſo to be ſanctified &amp; vpright, as that, in as much as hee dealeth with the Lords oracles, he mangle not, nor wryth or wreſt the Scripture,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.15.</note> but cut it aright, as the prieſts, vnder the law, did the things, which were offered and ſacrificed. To conclude, ſeeing an euill ende dooth make the beſt actions, that may be, abominable, if the Goſpell be taught of enuie, of vaine glory, of flattery,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.15.</note> or miſapplied by ſuch ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter intents or purpoſes, then it is not handled according to the nature or dignitie of ſo heauenly a doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, but abuſed and polluted by mans corruption.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe as the teachers of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14627:31"/>Goſpell ought by ſo much the more faithfully and watchfully deale in the Lords oracles, by how much the myſterie of Chriſtian Religion ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleth the pollicie of the Iewes: ſo the hearers of the doctrine of chriſt Ieſus ought by ſo much the more attentiuely hearken vnto,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.1.</note> and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently receiue the meſſage of their Miniſters, by how much greater grace is offered vnto them now, than was in olde time to the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites. For if euery tranſgreſsion and breach of the Law, receiued a iuſt recompence of rewarde, how ſhall they then eſcape, if they neglect ſo great ſaluation, as is offered in the Goſpell? They are therefore to know, that they are not to heare ſuch as teach any falſe Chriſts, or denie the foundation of Chriſtian Religion, either expreſſely or by conſequence. For they are not ſo
<pb facs="tcp:14627:32"/>much as to goe out vnto them, they are not to bid them God ſpeed, not to receiue them to houſe,<note place="margin">2 Ioh. 1.10.</note> neither yet to thinke them otherwiſe than accurſed.<note place="margin">Gal. 8</note> Secondly, they are to heare all thoſe, who truely teach Chriſt Ieſus crucified, without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring of perſons for outward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, or holding on <hi>Paul, Cephas,</hi> or <hi>Apollos.</hi> But eſpecially they are to heare,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.12</note> reuerence, and ordinarilie to reſort vnto, thoſe ordinary ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t preachers, which the Lord in his prouidence hath placed ouer them. <hi>Obey</hi> (ſaieth the Apoſtle to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes) <hi>your guides,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.7.</note> 
               <hi>and ſubmit your ſelues vnto them: for they watch for your ſoules, that they may doo this with ioy, and not with ſorrowe, for that is vnprofitable for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how doo they obey their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie watchfull teachers, who do not ſo much as vſe to heare them
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14627:32"/>ſcant once in a month, nay in a twelue moneth? <hi>We beſeech you bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren</hi> (ſaieth <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>) <hi>acknowledge thoſe who trauella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; rule ouer you in the Lord, and admoniſh you, and eſteeme them more than moſt exceedinglie, as deare vnto you, for their work ſake.</hi> Let ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all ſo account of their ordinary teachers, as <hi>Paul</hi> aduiſed the <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians</hi> to eſteeme thoſe Paſtors or Preachers which laboured among them and as the <hi>Philippians</hi> ſtood af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected toward <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> their peculiar ſhepheard, whome the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle made haſt to ſend back vnto them, that they at the very ſight of him might reioyce. For what? Is the Miniſter bound, trowe we,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.28.</note> and commanded by God, ordinarily to teach, and to expound the word and is the hearer priuiledged from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorting vnto his ſermons diligently,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.25</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:14627:33"/>and ioyning with him in publique praiers? Shall the bloud of the flock be required at the ſhepheards hands, if he bee dumbe, or ſlothfull: and hangeth there no woe ouer the head of the ſheepe,<note place="margin">Ezech. 33.9</note> if they ſtray out of the folde, or refuſe to heare the voyce of their ſhepheard? Dooth the louing Wife preferre her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band in loue before all other, how beautifull ſoeuer? Dooth the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour waite vpon his Captaine, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though other in the hoſt be ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than he? Dooth the ſeruant at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend on his Maſter, albeit others are more honorable? Finally, doth the Child keepe in, and like beſt of his fathers houſe, notwithſtanding, that there be many, which keepe better tables? And wil not Chriſtians, like beſt of their ordinarie teachers, and cleaue vnto their peculiar and alot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Miniſters, albeit they perceiue
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14627:33"/>in them ſome wants or infirmities, or ſee greater graces or giftes ſhine in the candles or ſtarres of other Churches.</p>
            <p>But moreouer, it is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for a profeſſor of the Goſpell to heare vſuallie his true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhepheard, and to proceede no further: but he muſt take heede al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, what hee heareth, as our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our exhorteth.<note place="margin">Col. 3.16</note> Yea and after what manner he heareth both him and other, hee muſt heare the Word, not fooliſhlie, but wiſely, applying euerie good Doctrine and exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to himſelfe; not careleſlie,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 2 13</note> bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reuerentie, as the Worde of GOD, and not of man: not ſenſeleſlie, but with feeling, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a delight therein,<note place="margin">2. Cor 7.7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with affection euerie tune thereof.</p>
            <p>Finally not doubtingly, but with faith,
<pb facs="tcp:14627:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>beleeuing that euerie promiſe,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.2.</note> and threatning of the word, ſhall ſurely come to paſſe. After ſuch a forte the people in <hi>Nehemiah</hi> his time heard the word both read,<note place="margin">Nch. 8.1. &amp;c.</note> opened, and applied by <hi>Ezra,</hi> and the <hi>Leuits.</hi> For then, whilſt the Lawe was in reading, the cares of all the people were attent; in the time of praier, they lifted vp their hands, and bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed downe their bodies. Finally, when the threatnings of the word were applied by Preaching, they fel a weeping; and when againe they were comforted by their teachers, they reioyced.</p>
            <p>But now, although our attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and reuerence ſhould exceede theirs,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.1.</note> (as the Apoſtle ſheweth) yet it is farre behinde the ſame. Nay what confuſion and irreuerence, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in euery congregation, it not to be ſeene amongſt vs? Doe not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14627:34"/>vſuallie (O irreligious times) ſome talke in the midſt of the exerciſes of Religion, ſome run out of the Church before the Sermon be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſome ſleep in their pewes, ſome turne the eyes of all vpon them by their ſtrange and masking appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell? Finally, almoſt all ſhew ſome ſigne of neglect or contempt of the word of God, or other? But to let theſe paſſe, the true Chriſtian hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, will not onely bee carefull to heare the word in a right manner, but to reſort therunto with an holy intent and affection. For as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſheweth,<note place="margin">Pro. 21.27.</note> 
               <hi>The ſacrifice of the wicked is abomination vnto the Lord: how much more, when he offereth it with an euill mind?</hi> The Chriſtian then deſireth the ſincere milke of the Word not to cauill at it, no, nor to knowe it onelie, but to growe thereby. This, (if it were conſidered,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.2.</note> as it ought to
<pb facs="tcp:14627:35"/>bee) would make thoſe, who often reſort to the hearing of Sermons, not onely talkers,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.26.</note> but practiſers of Religion, not onely diſcerners, but haters of ſinne,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.104.</note> not onely ſuch as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in good exerciſes, but perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of holie dueties,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.9.</note> not praiſers onelie of their teachers in wordes, but commenders of them by their liues and conuerſations.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.1 2</note> For in deede he is the beſt hearer, which waſhing his ſpecks and ſpottes by the Lawe of libertie, is by hearing tranſformed into the image of Chriſt, and hee moſt commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his teacher, whoſe heart and life is written and grauen with the letters of faith and repentance.</p>
            <p>Now to come to the laſt point or note of the excellencie of the Goſpell, it is affirmed here to bee great <hi>by one aſſent.</hi> True it is in deed that a great number of prophane
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14627:35"/>people, make no account of the Goſpell, being either Dogges or Swine,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.6.</note> deſpiſing and abuſing pearles and holy things. But as concerning the true members of the Churche, euerie one of them with heart and hand ſubſcribeth to this Doctrine, ſo that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as <hi>Eſay</hi> notablie expreſsing this matter hath foretolde, <hi>This man ſaieth I am the Lordes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 44.5.</note> 
               <hi>and this man calleth himſelfe by the name of Iaacob, another writeth with his hand, I am the eternals, and nameth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by the name of Iſrael.</hi> Euident it is alſo,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.1</note> that manie Heretickes haue oppugned, and doo denie the verie articles of our faith. But what the inſtruments of Satan ſay or gainſay, is not to be regarded. This is that, which here our Apoſtle would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, namely that al the Lords faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; meſſengers haue with
<pb facs="tcp:14627:36"/>one voyce receiued and publiſhed, and are with their liues and bloud ready to ſeale the truth of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. To conclude, it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied that there are diuers truthes in the word,<note place="margin">Ro. 14.1, 2.</note> which true Chriſtians with one conſent yeeld not alwaies vnto. For either they vary one from another in the expoſition of ſome places of Scripture, or they differ in iudgement about queſtions of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes or vnlawfulnes,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.31, 32, 33.</note> of order or diſorder,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11. chapters.</note> or they diſſent in ſome inferiour points of trueth (If I maie ſo ſpeake) which yet are not to bee oppugned,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.19</note> yea are by all meanes on the contrarie ſide to be imbraced,<note place="margin">Exo. 10.26</note> held faſt, and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before golde or ſiluer, or the whole World. But oftentimes it is to be ſeene, that euen thoſe, who in interpretations of certaine ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences in the word,<note place="margin">Act. 15.39.</note> and in opinions
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14627:36"/>touching things lawfull or vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full differ furtheſt aſunder, concur and conſent together moſt nerely and fully in the Articles of the faith, the principles of the Goſpell, and all the fundamentall grounds of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion. Whereby it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that the vnitie of the members of the Catholick Church conſiſteth not in thinking the ſame things al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, or liking the ſame perſons, but in the generall conſent,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.13.</note> which is giuen vnto the myſterie of Chriſt Ieſus. In deede all are to labour to the vnitie of the ſpirit, to iudge and ſpeake euen al one thing;<note place="margin">1. Cor 11.19</note> but in this world ſuch a perfect knot ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be knit. But although Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans diſagree ſometime in affections or opinions: yet there is alwaies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them ſound vnitie in deede,<note place="margin">Ro. 12.4.5</note> becauſe they maintaine one maine veritie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14627:37"/>
            <p>Neither by reaſon of diuiſions, which muſt be, and haue been in al ages, among beleeuers and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Goſpell, is there iuſt cauſe giuen vnto any to departe from the Church of GOD, or to doubt whether there bee at all any certaine ſauing trueth, or to ſaye, there are ſuch diſſentions in the World, that a man cannot knowe what to beleeue. The Virgin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Simeon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 1, 2, 3. chap.</note> 
               <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples ſaw the ſauing and the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine trueth, when the ſinagogue of the Iewes erred euen touching the Meſsias, and was diuided into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers moſt peſtilent and contrarie ſects. The Chriſtians in the daies of the auncient Fathers ſawe the truth, and walked in the right way, when the <hi>Arrians, Eutichians,</hi> and ſuch other Heretickes ſpread their poyſon throughout the whole
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14627:37"/>world. Now then, to doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there bee any certaine trueth, (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the articles of the faith are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by one aſſent, and the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>England, France, Scotland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Har. con. apolo. eccl. Angl.</note> and the Lowe Countries ſubſcribe vnto the Doctrine of the Goſpell, and when manie Martyres haue of late ſealed the Doctrine of faith with their bloud, yea diuers liuing Martyrs confirme the ſame by word and deede) is to call into queſtion, whether there be a Sun in the Skie, and to doubt whether it ſhine in the firmament at noone day.</p>
            <p>Thus wee ſee the former parte of this ſentence laide open before our eyes, wherein that excellencie of the Goſpell is by ſixe wordes plainelie affirmed, the which in the ſecond part of this verſe is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed or prooued effectuallie by ſixe forcible reaſons. All theſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:14627:38"/>together with the former words, may briefelie be caſt after this ſort into one frame of proofe, whereby the whole matter intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of in this ſentence may yet more euidently be declared and more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concluded.</p>
            <list>
               <item>That trueth, wherein is ſhowed and whereby is prooued that God hath been manifeſted in the fleſh, iuſtified in the ſpirit, ſeene of Angels, preached a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the nations, beleeued in the world, and receiued vp in glorie, is great by one aſſent and without all coutrouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</item>
               <item>The myſterie of godlynes is that truth, wherein al theſe things are ſhewed, and whereby they are demonſtrated.</item>
               <item>The mysterie of godlynes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14627:38"/>is great by one aſſent and without all controuerſie.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The laſt part of this reaſon hath in the beginning of this ſentence been ſet down, which ought not to ſeeme ſtrange vnto any, namelie that the concluſion is ſet in the firſt or ſecond place, ſeeing this is an v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall thing both in the Scriptures, and in all good Writers.</p>
            <p>The middle part of the proofe is contained and expreſſed in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of this ſentence, which now we are to proceede vnto and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. The firſt part of the ſillogiſme is included in the laſt words of the verſe going before, wherein was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, that the whole Church of God vpholdeth this excellent truth. Now although the Apoſtle had not inſinuated any ſuch matter, as that the trueth, which teſtifieth or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimeth
<pb facs="tcp:14627:39"/>ſuch wonderfull and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable things, as here are ſet down, is great by one aſſent, or without controuerſie: yet this is ſo cleare a a point, that it ſeemeth to bee writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the beames of the ſunne, &amp; not to neede any further ſpeach or proofe.</p>
            <p>To the end then we may not goe about to light a candle, where it ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth clearely &amp; brightly, but be led forward (as it were) to perfection, and to the ende wee may the better vnderſtand, this chiefe principle of Chriſtian Religion, <hi>God hath beene manifested in the fleſh,</hi> let vs a while conſider the nature of the heauenly godhead. As co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the power, wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.19.</note> &amp; Maieſty of the godhead, it is in ſome part or ſort made known vnto vs by the creatures, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by the Scriptures. Wherefore whoſoeuer ſhall ſay with <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>I
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14627:39"/>knowe not God,</hi> ſhall ſhew himſelfe herein a lier, or a prophane perſon. But as touching the nature or form of the Lords being,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.16.</note> it is a thing ſo incomprehenſible in it ſelfe, that men are by no meanes able fullie to vnderſtand it: yea, without Chriſt they cannot (ſaue onelie in ſmall meaſure, &amp; darke manner) conceiue what it is. For that knowledge of God, which is conueighed into me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> onelie by certaine titles giuen him, or by the creatures, is bur ſuch a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauing of his Maieſtie, as the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes of things in this world,<note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.20</note> leade the minde vnto, and ingender. As for example, when the Lord is called <hi>the Lord of Hosts,</hi> in this title we ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſee his works than him, or if wee ſee him in any meaſure, it is by the helpe of earthlie creatures, &amp; by compariſon, (as it were) not ſimply by himſelfe. Againe, when we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb facs="tcp:14627:40"/>him as perfectly wiſe, iuſt &amp; mercyfull,<note place="margin">Act. 14.16, 17.</note> wee rather rife to the knowledge of his effects, than of his being, by the conſideration of theſe vertues, which being in men by meaſure, are properties and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities onelie, howſoeuer being in GOD without meaſure, they are things eſſentiall.<note place="margin">Exod. 3.14.</note> Now as touching, the great titles of <hi>Iehoua,</hi> the eternal, I am, or I will bee, and ſuch like, whereby God in ſcripture is often called, they ſhew by thoſe creatures, which are ſubſtances, mouing and ſubſiſting in the World,<note place="margin">Reu. 1.4.</note> that the Lord hath a being by himſelfe, and for himſelfe, but that he is a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, infinite, vnchangeable, &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious eſſence, cannot ſo well be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by the ſight of fraile,<note place="margin">1. Per. 1.24</note> mutable and baſe creatures, as is manifeſted by Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">The goſpel of Iohn. 1 18 Heb. 13.8</note> both God and man, who is the ſame to day and to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14627:40"/>and for euer, and in whome the whole Godhead dwelleth bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily.</p>
            <p>Neither in deed ariſeth vnto man any ſparke of ſound comfort at all,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.18.</note> out of the beholding of the nature of the godhead alone,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.1.</note> as it is ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally or confuſedly conſidered by it ſelfe without. Chriſt, but rather ſo gliſtering a light and flame is able to cauſe the moſt ſtrong and pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing eye in the world to dazle, and the moſt hardie and valiant hear to quake for horror. Wherefore we are alwaies, when wee turne our fight toward the Godhead, with a certaine reuerent and diſcerning ſpirit, to looke vpon three perſons hauing their being therein, as vpon three Sunnes in one,<note place="margin">Mat. 2.19.</note> (it I may ſo ſpeake with that profound diuine <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> who oft moſt ſingular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly writeth of this matter) all of the
<pb facs="tcp:14627:41"/>ſame nature, glorie, eternitie, and perfection.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe perſons is the father,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.17.</note> who as he is without all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, ſo this perſon cauſed from eternitie the two other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> and this father worketh from himſelfe by his ſonne, and by his ſpirit. The ſecond perſon is the ſonne, who, as he was eternally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by the perſon of the Father only:<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.16. Heb. 1.3.</note> ſo from him as the fountaine, being himſelfe as the ſtreame, hee worketh by the holy Ghoſt, as the conduit pipe (if that I may ſo ſpeak) and by earthly things in ſome rude ſort ſhadoweth out theſe heauenly, which nothing in the World can fully or in all reſpects repreſent or expreſſe?<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.26.</note> The holy Ghoſt is the third perſon in trinitie, proceeding from the Father, and the ſonne, &amp; working from them both immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atlie,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14627:41"/>by himſelf, in ſuch ſort, as that not onely he quickeneth the whole worlde, but ſanctifieth the whole Church. For he, euen he, repleniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with graces the Angels, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpireth the Prophets, hee teacheth the Lawgiuers wiſedom,<note place="margin">Baſil. ho. mil. de ſide.</note> he ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the Miniſters of the word, he maketh Captaines valiant, he abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the innocent, hee aduaunceth thoſe that are modeſt, hee worketh gifts of healing, hee reuiueth the dead, hee looſeth the captiues, hee maketh ſtrangers children by adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It he finde a beleeuing Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, he maketh him an Euangeliſt. If he be in a Fiſher man, he frameth him to be a Diuine. If he get a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant perſecutor, hee appoynteth and faſhioneth him to bee an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of the Gentiles, a preacher of the Goſpell, an elect veſſell. By him the weake are made ſtrong, the poore
<pb facs="tcp:14627:42"/>rich, the ignorant and thoſe which are void of eloquence become euen wiſer than the wiſeſt. Al the which workes with infinite more are alſo wrought by the Father &amp; the Son,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.17</note> and not onely by the holie Ghoſt: but as theſe three perſons are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct in properties, which cannot be communicated to each other, as the Father, in that he is vnbegotten, the Sonne begotten, the holy Ghoſt proceeding: ſo they differ in the manner or order of their workes, which in common they put into execution,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.6.</note> ſeeing the Father begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the worke from himſelfe, the Sonne worketh it from the Father by the ſpirit, the holie Ghoſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth it from them both by his owne immediat hand, and laſt ſtitch as it were.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the name of <hi>God</hi> in this place, as elſewhere in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14627:42"/>is reſtrained to the ſecond per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Trinitie, namely the Son, withdrawing our eyes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the two other perſons, and onely fixing our ſight vpon this lampe of all our ioy, and garland of our comfort, let vs conſider a little longer his eternall generation or begetting. For when here it is ſaid, that <hi>God hath been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted in the fleſh,</hi> the meaning of the Apoſtle is not that either the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or the ſpirit euer tooke our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on them: but onely that Chriſt the naturall and eternall ſonne of God, taking to himſelfe the ſeede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> was ſubiect vnto all humane infirmities, ſinne ouely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. After the like manner by this our Apoſtle is the name of God being common to all the three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſo vſed in the <hi>Acts,</hi> as that it is onely meant of the ſecond perſon, when he willeth the Elders of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus
<pb facs="tcp:14627:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>to feed the Church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his owne bloud.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> But, I ſay, before wee come to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the conception or birth of Chriſt, the which had a beginning in time, order requireth that in the former place we view his heauenly generation or begetting from alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie.</p>
            <p>The author of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> calling this ſecond per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>the brightnes of his fathers glorie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> declareth, that euen as the Sunne in the Skie naturallie begetteth the bright beame: ſo GOD the father not onely of his will, but by nature begat his Sonne, the bright beame of this glorie. The ſame Apoſtle cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth alſo the Sonne of God, <hi>the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen image of his fathers perſon,</hi> euen as the Lord himſelf in <hi>Exodus</hi> termeth him the Angel <hi>in whom his name is written:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. 23.21.</note> no doubt, becauſe the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14627:43"/>of the Father is wholly imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in, &amp; expreſſed by the perſon of the Sonne. In ſome ſuch like ſenſe by our <hi>Paule</hi> to the <hi>Coloſsians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1.15.</note> hee is termed the image of the inuiſible God, his father, whom indeede hee doth ſo reſemble, and ſo liuelie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent in all reſpects, that rather he ſeemeth the ſame with his father, than like vnto him, being herein vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like vnto naturall children of this world, in that they in part only are like vnto their mortall parents, but he in eternitie, nature and vertue is whollie like, or rather one with his heauenly father. Wherefore <hi>Iohn</hi> in his Goſpell fitlie calleth him <hi>the onely begotten of his father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.18</note> of whom onely, as he was begotten, ſo was he begotten after an only manner, and therfore he loueth him with an on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie loue, and in him onely is well pleaſed. In this reſpect <hi>Salomon</hi> in
<pb facs="tcp:14627:44"/>that excellent booke of the <hi>Prouerbs</hi> very elegantlie nameth this ſonne the daylie delight or ioye of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, affirming that he is one,<note place="margin">Pro. 1.30.</note> which nouriſheth and cheareth vp, or ſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth before him continually, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all eternitie the ſweet word in his boſome, ſuch a louely branch of beautie, and flower of delight, as that it is impoſsible that any earthly parents ſhould take ſuch pleaſure in the ſweet lookes, moſt wittie ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or vertuous actions of their onely childe, as the eternall GOD is well pleaſed or ſolaceth himſelfe in this his ſonne. Howbeit, this eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall generation alſo euen of the <hi>Sonne</hi> or <hi>Word,</hi> being viewed in any ſhape of glorie, or other nature than of man,<note place="margin">Eſa. 6.5.</note> is able to make the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> himſelfe crie out, <hi>Woe is me, for I am cut off, ſeeing I am a man of pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted lips.</hi> And that the manifeſting
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14627:44"/>of this ſecond perſon vnto man in any ſhape of glorie or power, rather offereth him occaſion to ſtande a loofe of, than to draw nere to God, it may appear by that caueat, which the ſonne of God giueth <hi>Moſes,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing into him in a fierie buſh, <hi>come not neere to this place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the end then,<note place="margin">Exod. 3.5.</note> that wee might haue the greater boldnes, and an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe vnto the throne of grace, full of hope and confidence, it pleaſed God, who is by nature inuiſible, to <hi>be manifeſted in the fleſh,</hi> as here the Apoſtle ſpeaketh. For had the ſonne of GOD remayned ſtill for euer onely an inuiſible perſon, fleſh and bloud neuer could or would with comfort haue approached to ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and infinite a Maieſtie, which it had moſt grieuouſlie offended,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.8.</note> &amp; wherein it perceiued no ſigne or pledge of reconciliation. Or had
<pb facs="tcp:14627:45"/>he taken on him the nature of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, which neuer he did, although by reaſon of the execution of his office, hee ſometimes in called in ſcripture by the name of an Angell) well might the elect Angels haue endured his preſence, or triumphed exceedinglie, or the damned ſpirits, which left their ſtanding places, lift vp their heads to ſome hope: but as for men, they ſhould ſtill haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in deſpaire and perplexitie, who, both haue been oft amaſed &amp; troubled aboue meaſure,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.17. Luk. 1.12.</note> when hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly powers or principalities haue appeared at any time vnto them, &amp; alway were only reuiued with this hope, that Chriſt ſhould not take vnto him the nature of Angels, but the ſeede of the woman, the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the ſeede of <hi>Dauid.</hi> Or againe, had the Lord ſpoken vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs by the voyce of thunder,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.18</note> or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14627:45"/>himſelf in the light, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe been manifeſted in the ſhape of any creature; the nature of man hauing offended, would not well be ſatiſfied, nor yet could bee reſtored. Finally, had he taken vnto him the noble nature of <hi>Adam,</hi> or put on him that princely condition, which man had before his tranſgreſsion, duſt and aſhes might with greefe haue remembred whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it had fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len: but ſuch ſound comfort or ſtrong hope, as now we feele,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.17.</note> could not ariſe vnto vs by that gay gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Wherefore our Sauiour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the forme of GOD, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting it no robberie to be equall with God, that the fruit might bee ours, the ſuffering his, hiding (as it were) for a time the brightneſſe of his Mareſtie, not regarding the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, which had fallen, would in his wonderful mercie and vnſpeakable
<pb facs="tcp:14627:46"/>humilitie put on him, not the forme of any other creature, not <hi>Adams</hi> royaltic, but the ragged coate of a poore ſeruant,<note place="margin">Pſal 2.5.</note> yea the weaknes and vilenes (as it were) of a worme.</p>
            <p>Oh,<note place="margin">Pſal 22.6.</note> what is that which now I doo behold? What? the grauen i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of Gods owne perſon &amp; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, printed within mine earthlie &amp; filthie ſtampe &amp; molde? What? the brightnes of the heauenlie glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and excellencie, dimmed and darkened with my frailtie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie? What? the eternall and moſt bleſſed ſonne of the higheſt, to become a worme and no man, an outcaſt of the people, &amp; a contempt of the nations? What? the Angell, in whom the name of God is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, paſsing ouer the Angels, which had offended, and leauing them all in the chaines of darknes, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they were of a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14627:46"/>nature and an higher degree; but taking compaſsion on ſinfull and wretched mankinde, made one with vs, or God with man, that the baſer creature ſhould bee made like an elect Angell? What? the onelie begotten and the ſweete ioy of the heauenlie palace, couered and gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded round about with my weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, thirſt, hunger, drowſineſſe, and ſuch like infirmities of bodie, nay with agonies, feares, paſsions, and affections of the ſoule? Oh where are yee now a daies yee Chriſtian hearers and profeſſors,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 11.</note> who deſire with the Prophets &amp; godly people of old time to ſee theſe miſteries vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded? or who thirſt euen with auncient Kinges and Princes to heare the doctrines or diſcourſes of the woorke of your redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?<note place="margin">Luk. 10.24</note> Nay, nay, where are you, ye skilfull and faithfull ſheapheards
<pb facs="tcp:14627:47"/>and teachers, who continuallie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound the praiſes of that chief ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of the Chriſtian flock,<note place="margin">Pſal. 24.</note> which cauſeth his ſheepe to lie downe in greene paſtures, and leadeth them by the calme waters? Come forth, and paint Chriſt Ieſus as crucified before the eyes of your people,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.1.</note> ſhew them the prince, valure and vertue of this myſterie. Neuertheleſſe, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer euen thoſe, whoſe hearts are furniſhed with moſt diuine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſhal come to handle this chief argument of Diuinitie, albeit they ſhall alſo ſpeake with the tongues of men or Angels: yet ſhall they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bee able fullie to declare or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold this one ſecrete of the incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Lorde, or by any ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſufficiently to ſhewe the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of this matter, which is moſt wonderfull in many reſpects. For who can but maruell, how the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14627:47"/>
               <hi>Marie</hi> ſhould bee the mother of the ſonne of God, and yet not onely bee a virgin before the conception,<note place="margin">Luk 5.14.</note> but a virgin at the conception, yea, a virgin after the conception of him? What reaſon of man can conceiue how the holie Ghoſt ſhould ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowe the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> in ſuch ſort, as that taking out of her the whole lumpe of the humane nature of Chriſt, by him it ſhould not only be ſeuered from all corruption, but vnited and knit vnto the diuine, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch an vnſpeakable and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible manner, as that a diuine nature and an humane conſiſting of a ſoule and bodie, ſhould vnſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rablie and eternallie be ioyned and concurre in one and the ſelfe ſame perſon the ſonne of the higheſt?</p>
            <p>But ſeeing we are conceaued and formed in ſinne, to the end, that not onely actuall iniquitie might bee
<pb facs="tcp:14627:48"/>waſhed away, but euen originall &amp; naturall vncleannes, cured and clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, it behoued the branch to ariſe out of the ſtock of <hi>Ieſſe,</hi> and a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to bee ſet open vnto the houſe of <hi>Dauid</hi> and the inhabitants of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> for the purging of ſinne: fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallie a ſcepter to be erected againſt the raigne of death, who medled with thoſe which neuer ſinned ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuallie, as <hi>Adam</hi> did.</p>
            <p>But the ſpeach by the Apoſtle here vſed is verie diligentlie to bee obſerued,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.14</note> namely that God not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie hath been in the fleſh, but that <hi>he hath been manifeſted in the fleſh.</hi> The which words import thus much, namely that the ſonne of God firſt conceaued in the virgins wombe, was afterward brought foorth into the worlde. Of this matter as the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> long before had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſelie and plainlie propheſied,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14627:48"/>ſaying in the perſon of all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that <hi>vnto vs a child is borne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>and vnto vs a ſonne is giuen:</hi> ſo it was meet and conuenient, that this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie light ſhould breake out as the Sunne, and the ſaluation of Gods people ſhine foorth, and be held vp as a burning lampe. For ſo long as this moſt excellent treaſure was hid in the wombe of the Virgin, the price or glorie of it not being ſeene, but ſhut vp (as it were) neither could the beautie of it (vnknowne as yet) bee earneſtlie and generallie deſired, neither could the vſe or fruit of it ſo well be felt, or ſo fullie be enioyed. But after that Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus once pight his tent amongſt vs for the time, neither onely lay in the maunger, but walked on the earth, the faithfull diſciples ſawe his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as the glorie of the onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of God, and beleeuers or Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb facs="tcp:14627:49"/>haue more fully ſince that time been made partakers of his grace.<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now, what a wonderfull thing againe is this to conſider, namelie, that the ancient of daies was borne in time: he, whom the heauens can not containe,<note place="margin">Naz.</note> did lie in a cratch; the preſeruer of all things did ſucke his mothers breaſt; the feeder of Iſrael hungred and thirſted; the only wiſe increaſed in wiſedome; hee, who knoweth al things, was ignorant of ſome things: finallie, the King of glorie became in all things like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man, ſinne only excepted? Theſe myſteries are maruellous indeede, but they are no leſſe comfortable than wonderfull, ſeeing now wee may behold the ſonne of GOD ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching vnto vs, not as a mightie giant with a barre of yron to breake vs all to peeces, not as an earthlie King or Captaine garded with an
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14627:49"/>hoſt of armed Soldiours to deſtroy vs, but as a childe, whom without feare wee may take in our armes, or as our naturall brother, in whome wee may acknowledge fleſh of our fleſh and one of our bones.<note place="margin">Heb. 2.17.</note> The lawe was indeed giuen with thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, &amp; with lightnings, with ſtorme and tempeſt, and the ſound of a tro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.18.</note> and it was pronounced out of the middeſt of a flaming fire: but as for the Goſpell, it was proclaymed without any ſigne of terrour at all, yea on the contrarie ſide, it began ſo to bee publiſhed and witneſſed by the Lords appearing and doctrine, as that God gaue teſtimonie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto with many wonders &amp; tokens of good will and mercie.</p>
            <p>The next point here offered by the Apoſtle to our conſideration is, that <hi>God hath been alſo iuſtified in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> Before hath bin ſhewed that the
<pb facs="tcp:14627:50"/>ſonne of God being in the forme of GOD, and equall to GOD, abaſed, emptied and humbled himſelfe, and drawing a curtaine (as it were) ouer his infinite Maieſtie, walked in the ſhape of a poore ſeruant, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted himſelfe to be alſo man in all poynts like to vs, ſinne onely excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Now, here is further declared, that the glorie of his diuine nature, power &amp; office, ſo ſhined through his fleſh, and through the courſe of his whole conuerſation, euen (as it were) through a glaſſe or a lanterne (if I may ſo ſpeake) that thereby ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared who he was, euen that Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour betweene GOD and man, that Meſsias or perſon annoynted with the oyle of gladnes aboue his fellowes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.7.</note> touching whom the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures foretolde and ſpake many honorable thinges, who alſo hath wrought the work of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14627:50"/>For, as the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth of him, <hi>the ſpirit of the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houa was vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa 61.1.</note> 
               <hi>yea the ſpirit of Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua rested on him:</hi> namely, the ſpirit of wiſdome &amp; of vnderſtanding, the ſpirit of comfort and of power,<note place="margin">Eſa. 11.2.</note> the ſpirit of knowledge &amp; of the ſcare of God.</p>
            <p>The ſonne of God being thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with the gifts of the ſpirite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue meaſure, being ſent, annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſealed, and conſecrated to the office of a Sauiour, the whole God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head dwelling in him bodilie: final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, he louing his Church moſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirelie, as the ſame Prophet teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, at the laſt put on righteouſnes as a breaſt-plate,<note place="margin">Eſa. 59.17.</note> and an helmet of ſaluation vpon his head, yea armed himſelfe with the garments of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance for clothing, and araied him ſelfe with zeale as with a cloake. Whereby may further be gathered
<pb facs="tcp:14627:51"/>after what ſort in this place, and in what reſpect the Meſsias beeing God and man is ſaid to be iuſtified by the ſpirit. In ſumme, thus much is ment, that the power of his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, being contrarie (in regarde of exceeding glorie) to the weake na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of his manhood, but ioyned therwithal, did not only inable him fully to performe the work of our ſaluation, but declare him to bee a perfect King, Prieſt &amp; Prophet, the fountaine of wiſedome, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſanctification and redemption. True it is indeede,<note place="margin">1. Co. 1.30</note> that, although in the daies of his fleſh, our Sauiour li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned moſt innocentlie, wrought ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miracles, ſpake and taught as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any did, yet the wicked, who were in thoſe daies, reiected &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned him. Neuertheleſſe, as the ſacred ſtorie declareth, not onelie wiſedome was iuſtified of her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but the ſame ſtone,<note place="margin">Luk. 20.17</note> which the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14627:51"/>builders refuſed, was by the father made the head corner ſtone: yea the ſonne in three daies builded vp that te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, where of <hi>Salomons</hi> temple was but a tipe: finally, the innocent liſe, the heauenly doctrine, the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſignes, the ſingular gifts of our Sauiour, wherewith he was indued without meaſure, prooued &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed to all the world, that euen that glorious ſpirit reſted on him,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.18 19.</note> which preached vnto the diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in the time of <hi>Noah,</hi> and which not only reuined him,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.4.</note> when he had been dead concerning the fleſh, but quickeneth all the elect to faith, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience,<note place="margin">Rom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.11.</note> and eternall life.</p>
            <p>Albeit then the weakenes of the fleſh of Chriſt was ſuch that he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be the moſt abiect of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea rather a worme than a man, as before we haue heard; yet the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his ſpirite was ſo great, on the contrarie ſide, that thereby he
<pb facs="tcp:14627:52"/>was declared not to be a meere man or an Angell, but the ſonne of God, and perfected vnto all the particular workes of a ſauing Prince or redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. He tooke vnto him the ſeede of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſtory of the goſ. pel.</note> but in this ſeede were all the nations of the earth bleſſed. Compaſſed he was in his mothers wombe, but <hi>Iohn the Baptiſt</hi> at his preſence ſprang in <hi>Elizabeths</hi> bellie. Laide hee was in a cratch, but wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped therein by the wiſe men of the Eaſt. Hee was baptized in <hi>Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan,</hi> but he baptized with the holie Ghoſt and with fire. Hee was hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie, but hee fed many thouſands: ſubiect to ſleepe, but he cauſed the windes and waues to couch: tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute hee paid, but out of a fiſh: hee wept for <hi>Lazarus,</hi> but he raiſed him from the dead. O rare &amp; moſt roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, O ſweete &amp; bountifull Sauiour, whether ſhould I rather wonder at
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14627:52"/>thy ſufferings, or at this thy glory? Surely at the ſight of thy mercie I ſtand aſtonied. <hi>Iudas</hi> ſelleth thee for a little paltrie ſiluer, but thou redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt the world with thy moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious heart bloud. O when I think vpon that night, wherein thou waſt betrayed: when I conceiue in minde thy ſweates like clots of bloud, rolling from thy bodie downe vnto the ground: when I beholde the officers, which kept thee, beating thy neck, and ſmiting thy tender face: when I look on the red furrowes, which <hi>Pilates</hi> cruell whip made on thy back: when I feele the print made in thine hands and feete with the nayles: when I ſee thy veynes and ſinewes ſtreyned and racked on the Croſſe: I plainely perceiue it was not without great cauſe, that thou didſt requeſt thy heauenly father, to let ſo bitter a cup
<pb facs="tcp:14627:53"/>paſſe from thee, if it had been poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. But when I view the burden of the ſinnes of the whole World laid on thy ſhoulders, when I mark the curſe of the Lawe ſeaſing on thine head, when I perceiue the wrath of thy Father conſuming all thy bones, when I obſerue the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutioners ſtripping thee out of all thy garments, when I note the Iewes with mocks and mowes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riding thine afflicted eſtate, when I conſider ſatan and the feends of hell in the malapart ſouldiers, the croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked herauld <hi>Pilate,</hi> and the vnrepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant malefactor aſſaulting thy faith: I cannot but cry out, O wonderfull redeemer, what a ſpirit of courage and long ſuffering reſted on thee? Now laſt of all when I heare thee crie, <hi>My God, my God, why haste thou forſaken mee,</hi> when I peere into thine heart pearced vnto the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14627:53"/>bottome with the Speare of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Souldiout, when I gaze on thy breath flying out of thy bodie, when I prie into the graue where thy body was layd, when I thinke on thine aboade in the earth for the ſpace of three dayes and three nights, reckoned in ſome ſorte, (after which manner, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to which time <hi>Ionas</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times lodged in the belly of the Whale) how doo I maruell, that thy father did not rather ſuffer the whole world to periſh, than thee his natural ſome, more precious than a thouſand worlds; to taſt or ſuſtaine one of the Ieaſt of theſe indignities? But here by appeareth the vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able mercy of God thy father, as alſo thine own exceeding loue &amp; fauor toward ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kinde, yea moreouer the glory of the ſpirit, which reſted on thee, that thou wouldſt endure ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:14627:54"/>torments for thine enemies, &amp; that thou wouldſt by thy Croſſe cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Worlde, by thy death kill ſinne, by thy buriall put the Lawe into the graue, by thine enduring of the curſe beſtowe a bleſsing, by thine aboad vnder the ground, take away the ſting of the graue; finallie, by all thy ſufferings ſatiſfie for all our ſinnes, and conquer him, who hath the power of death,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.14.</note> to wit, the Diuell.</p>
            <p>Now hereby it is euident, that he of whom we ſpeake, was not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man but God; not only the ſonne of man, but the ſonne of GOD; not onely a ſeruant, but the Lorde; not onely a ſhepheard, but a Prince of peaces finallie the way the truth, the life, the vine, the head of the church and that iuſt one, who was iuſtified by the ſpirit. For had there been in Chriſt Ieſus any dram of ſinne or
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14627:54"/>corruption, nay had there not been in him all fulnes of power and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, ſo many crimes and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions being laide to his charge, and imputed vnto him before the tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſeate of Almightie GOD, and ſuch principalities and powers pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing and aſſaulting him, neither could he haue been acquitted as an innocent perſon, nor eſcape as a ſtronger champion than all his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries. But becauſe there was no guile found in his mouth, and his own right hand being able to ſaue him, hee did caſt abroad the indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of his wrath vppon his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and infinitly ſurpaſsing <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> in ſtrength, ouercame the gates of hell; hee became that iuſt one, which iuſtifieth many, and that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect redeemer, who hauing been a faithful mediator on earth, raigneth now as a glorious high Prieſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> king
<pb facs="tcp:14627:55"/>and Prophet in Heauen as exalted for theſe iniuries done vnto him, and iuſtified alſo by the glory beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed on him.</p>
            <p>The third poynt of this myſterie is, that God manifeſted in the fleſh, and iuſtified, in the Spirit, <hi>hath been alſo ſeene of Angels.</hi> It appeareth by the ſacred ſtorie, that euen the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Angels, or vncleane ſpirits ſaw the ſonne of God manifeſted in the fleſh.<note place="margin">Mat. 4.1.</note> For we reade that not only ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan their head, tempted him in the wildernes, but that a whole legion of foule feends acknowledged him to be the ſonne of God,<note place="margin">Luk. 8.28.</note> and iudge of the World. Wherefore euen the euill Angels ſawe Ieſus our Lord, as the ſeede of the Woman, who ſhould breake the head of the Serpent, as a Champion to wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle or incounter with them; laſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14627:55"/>of all, as a conquerour by his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and ſtrength to ouercome them.</p>
            <p>But either only or chiefely Saint <hi>Paul</hi> meaneth here, that the Elect Angels ſaw Chriſt as viſible GOD, or as both GOD and man. Theſe heauenly ſpirites from the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of their creation, enioyed in deede the preſence of the ſecond perſon in the Trinitie,<note place="margin">Eſa. 6 3.</note> yea and they worſhipped him as their GOD and King: neuertheleſſe they wanted the viſible ſpectacle of the glorie here ſpoken of, vntill the time of the Lords incarnation and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation to the World, and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification by the Spirit. But when once the Father brought his firſt begotten into the World, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented him in the fleſh, as a mirrour of all wiſdome, mercie, iuſtice, and
<pb facs="tcp:14627:56"/>perfect excellencie; then the Angels in the ſonne, whoſe perſon &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head from the beginning of their creation they beheld continuallie, ſaw that humaine nature and glory,<note place="margin">Ephe. 3.10.</note> which before was neuer ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their view.<note place="margin">Heb. 1.6.</note> For they ſaw now the inuiſible word to become viſible God, they perceiued alſo the world to be made ſubiect not vnto them, but vnto man,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.5, 6 7, 8, 9.</note> euen the mediator between God and man, that ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> Ieſus Chriſt. After this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner at the laſt, in fulnes of time, the ſonne of God being, preſented vnto the view of the Elect Angels, they ſaw him as their ioye, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, in that they ſang at his birth:<note place="margin">Luk. 2.13.</note> they ſaw him as their Lord, vppon whom they aſcended,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.25.</note> &amp; deſcended, they ſaw him as the head of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of the Church,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.14.</note> whoſe members they ſerue: laſt of all they ſaw him
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14627:56"/>as the mercy ſeate, toward which they turne their faces continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.<note place="margin">Exo. 25.17, 18.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And who is there now, which remembring that ſolemne day of Chriſt his incarnation, beholding the Pageant (as I may ſay) of his humaine nature, whereat the very Angels gaze and aſſemble, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, conſidering the progreſſe, (as it were) of the Lord from Heauen to earth, together with his returne from earth to Heauen (where the Angels continually behold his face, and now enioy his bodily preſence) would not ſkip for ioy with <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, crie out with <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> inlarge his tongue with <hi>Zacharie,</hi> magnifie the Lord with the Virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> deſire to bee diſſolued with <hi>Simeon,</hi> and prouoke not onelie his owne ſoule, but the Angels to praiſe GOD with <hi>Dauid,</hi> for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting
<pb facs="tcp:14627:57"/>ſuch a ſpectacle to the view of his creatures, and reuealing his ſonne both vnto men and ſpirites.</p>
            <p>When as the common people of any countrey or kingdome, firſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding the kings inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to make ſome progreſſe, or to ſolace and ſhew himſelf abroad, afterward vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this occaſion reſort or flock, to the place where hee paſſeth by or may beſt be ſeen, there doo ſee his Maieſties face, or heare him vtter a few words: herein they thinke a great part of their happines to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, and hereof they boaſt full oft one to another: not without iuſt cauſe. For certainely the very coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and preſence of the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſoueraigne, carieth with it the Maieſtie of God himſelfe, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of an Angell, the glorie of the ſunne, the comelines of the moone, the brightnes of a Start, the bleſsing
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14627:57"/>of the dew, the fruit of a tree of life, and (to ſpeake in one Word) the price of a peerleſſe pearle. Now the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when as the immortall king, the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of all princes preſented himſelfe to the view of ſhepheards, wiſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Galileans,</hi> inhabitants of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> &amp; diuers other of his meaner ſorte of ſubiects, albeit they ſaw his face but for a little time, or heard his words but for a ſhort ſeaſon, this was a iuſt cauſe to them of ſingular comfort, and a great ſigne of his fauour, yea, as a day or time of high ſolemnitie. But doth not then the magnificence of the Lord on the one ſide, and the happines of the Angels, on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, much more appeare herein, that ſince they as peeres of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly kingdom were firſt aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled &amp; drawn vnto their prince Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, putting on him the nature of man and comming into the world,
<pb facs="tcp:14627:58"/>they haue not ceaſed to beholde and enioy his corporall preſence, and now ſitting (as it were) in court or Parliament with him continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, ſee his royaltie, and heare him ſpeake ſuch ſpeeches, as no eare of man hath heard, nor heart can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue. Yes happie ſure are all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, which are ſubiects to Chriſt Ieſus, &amp; ſee him by the eye of faith, though not of the body: more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie are the Angels, which ſtand e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer before him, and heare his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Moſt bleſſed bee the Lorde God the father, which ſo loued his ſonne, as to ſet him one the throne of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe the Lord loued <hi>Iſrael</hi> for euer, and made him king to doo equitie and righteouſnes.</p>
            <p>From this loue of GOD it hath proceeded alſo, that <hi>Christ Ieſus hath beene preached among the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> The Angels, of whome wee
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14627:58"/>ſake a little before, were not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beholders of Chriſt Ieſus, but Heralds, who blazed abroad his armes, and proclaymed the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of his conception, birth, reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and aſcention. Next after Iohn the baptiſt, the Lord himſelfe, &amp; the Angels, ſucceeded the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and ſeuentie diſciples, who all were immediately called by our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour himſelf to preach the word &amp; to work miracles,<note place="margin">Luk. 9.1. Luk. 10.1.</note> &amp; were ſent not to one place or congregation onely; but the 12. Apoſtles to many natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, the 70. diſciples to many cities: as our ſauiours commaundement and their practiſe teſtifieth.</p>
            <p>After theſe ſeuentie and beſides the twelue Apoſtles; the Lorde extraordinarilie rayſed vp and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in mercy to the forenamed la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers in his harueſt, Euangeliſts: and theſe againe were of two ſorts:
<pb facs="tcp:14627:59"/>for ſome of them penned ſtories of the goſpell,<note place="margin">Act. 21.8 1 Tim. 4.5 Act. 11.28.</note> as Luke and Marke: ſome onely publiſhed the goſpell by preaching, as Timothie and Phillip. At the ſame time were alſo Prophets rayſed vp, indued with an extraordinarie gift of fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telling things to come, as <hi>Agabus.</hi> But becauſe, neither the extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie giftes of ſuch Apoſtles, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſts, and Prophets, were alwaies to remaine in the Church, neither coulde their perſons bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mortall, continue in the Worlde for euer, ordinarie meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers or Miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, called both by GOD and man, and allotted to one place, were by the Apoſtles them ſelues created and ordayned in their time, who inſtructed ſome of them the Church of <hi>Lystra,</hi> ſome of <hi>Ico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium,</hi> ſome of <hi>Antiochia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 14.24.</note> ſome
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14627:59"/>the Churche of <hi>Epheſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 2, 3. chap.</note> ſome the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> ſome of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> ſome of <hi>Phillippi,</hi> ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther congregations.<note place="margin">Phillip. 1.1</note> This kinde of Preachers of the Word hauing continued from the Apoſtles times, and beeing to remaine to the ende of the Worlde haue ſpread the fame of the Goſpell ſo farre and neere, and ſo planted and watred it in their Countries and charges, as that not onely by the Apoſtles Miniſterie, but hence it commeth to paſſe, that there are many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in the Worlde at this day, many congregations profeſsing the trueth, yea many Countries imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Chriſt Ieſus, as namely, <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie, France, England, Scotland, Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke,</hi> with many other renowned in this reſpect. Wherefore the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel hath been preached not onely in <hi>Iudea,</hi> but among the natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as here
<pb facs="tcp:14627:60"/>is ſaide, neither vnto a few nations, but what people almoſt is there, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome of whom at one time or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſame of Chriſt Ieſus hath not been brought alter ſome ſort or manner at the leaſt?</p>
            <p>In deed euen before the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the ſonne of God into the world, the Iewes had among them thoſe ſhadowes, which couered ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning light; and thoſe Prophets, who ſpake in their hearing of the Meſsias, to come. Moreouer the Gentiles had ſometime meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Prophets ſent vnto them, as may appeare in <hi>Ionas,</hi> who prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to the <hi>Niniuites;</hi> but ſince that Chriſt Ieſus hath beene manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in the fleſhe, the Goſpell hath both been more plainelie and ſullie made knowne to the Iſraelites than before, and generallie in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon imparted and communicated
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14627:60"/>vnto other nations. For the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wall hauing been puld downe by him,<note place="margin">Col. 2.14.</note> that maketh one of two, and the bonds of the lawe cancelled by his ſufferings, who ſacrificed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for the whole world, al nations were to bee called to the Paſſeouer which had been ſlaine, and the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall pardon of forgiuenes of ſinnes was to bee offered vnto all ſortes of people. Well then, neither did the Lord ſuffer the ſtiffenecked Iewes to be without a great light, nor the Gentiles to remaine without the knowledge of Chriſt Ieſus: but he cauſed him to be preached to Iewe and Gentile; male and female, bond &amp; free, to ſhew that he would haue all ſorts of people to come vnto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and to be ſaued.</p>
            <p>So that hereby it is euident that the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt ſpeaketh farre more excellent and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb facs="tcp:14627:61"/>things, than did the bloud of <hi>Abel.</hi> For what is the voyce there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but <hi>Come vnto me al you which are heauie lade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11.28.</note> &amp; <hi>I wil refreſh you. Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it your ſinnes were as crimſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>they ſhall be like to ſnowe, although they were as ſcarlet, they ſhalbe like the wool.</hi> What interceſsion maketh it to God the father,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.52.</note> but <hi>Father forgiue them they knowe not what they doo, holie father preſerue them in thy name, ſanctifie them in thy trueth. Father it is my will that thoſe whom thou haſt giuen me, be with me where I am.</hi> To conclude, what things ſpeaketh the bloud of Chriſt to men, but ſuch as are moſt comfortable and ſound to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. I haue waſhed away the hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous rebellion and blaſphemie of diuers of thoſe Iewes, who indeed crucified the King of glorie:<note place="margin">Act. 2.37, 38</note> but for this bloudie deede vnfainedlie and heartilie repented. I haue cleanſed
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14627:61"/>and ſanctified a whole clowde of penitent ſinners among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, which ſometimes worſhipped Idols,<note place="margin">Leui. 18.24.</note> offered their children vnto <hi>Molech,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deu. 18.11.</note> vſed necromancie, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after ſouthſayers, and witches, exerciſed curious Artes,<note place="margin">Act. 18.19. 1. Theſ. 1.9.</note> were laden with all ſorts of impieties and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, &amp; quite dead in their ſinnes. Seeing theſe or ſuch like are the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gred words and promiſes, which the bloud of Chriſt Ieſus ſpeaketh and applieth vnto the heart of his Ieruſalem and people; how can any diſtreſſed and bruſed ſoule imagine that the God of mercie will deſpiſe the ſacrifice of ſorowe and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſupplications, which it offereth? Who will now adde vnto his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther innumerable iniquities this the greateſt of all other, no to beleeue his Sauiour: who hath not onely promiſed to ſaue him, but confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:14627:62"/>his promiſe by oth, not onelie ſworne ſo to doo, but ſealed his oth with bloud; not only aſſured in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a broad ſeale, but teſtified it by infinite example? To conclude this poynt, <hi>he which truſteth in the ſonne of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.10.</note> ſaith Saint Iohn, <hi>hath that wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in himſelfe, he which beleeueth not God, maketh him a lier.</hi> Well, if any want faith or the feeling thereof, here we ſee by the Lords ordinance that the preaching of the word is the moſt principall and moſt effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall meanes of ingrafting and nouriſhing the ſame. For how did ſo many thouſands in the Apoſtles times come vnto faith,<note place="margin">Ro. 10.14.</note> but by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the glad tidings of the Goſpell? How did they heare theſe ioyfull glad tidings, but by their teachers preaching among them? How did certaine choice meſſengers and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God preach to the reſt, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14627:62"/>that with ſo happie ſucceſſe, but by the Lords ſending them on his em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage, and bleſsing his owne holy and heauenlie ordinance? Priuate perſons neither were in auncient times, neither now are licenſed or permitted by the Lord, to bee Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Apoſtles, or Paſtors to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or to another.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.29.</note> The publique Miniſters of the worde, are thoſe, whom the Lord hath ſet apart, to bee ſtewards ouer the houſehold of faith,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.1.</note> his veſſells and meſſengers to carrie and declare the doctrine of faith: finallie, his vnder-officers to ſet on the ſeales of faith. Priuate conference, priuate prayer, priuate reading of the ſcriptures, are indeed verie profitable exerciſes of faith, when they are vſed together with the publike miniſterie of the word and continuallie quickened by the ſame. For the preaching of the
<pb facs="tcp:14627:63"/>word is ſo liuelie and mightie in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, that it is not onely as ſeede to beget men to ſaluation, but as milke to nouriſh them in faith and obedience, as wine to cheare them in diſtreſſe, as honie to delight the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as golde to enrich them, as a light to direct them; but alſo as a fire to kindle them vnto mutuall confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,<note place="margin">Luk. 24.32.</note> to earneſt praier, and to dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſearching of the ſcriptures. But when the publike Miniſterie ſhall bee ſo ſeuered from theſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate exerciſes as the ſoule is from the bodie, and as that it ſhall wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie bee neglected,<note place="margin">Luke. 7.30, 31.</note> refuſed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned by any; certainlie ſuch as deſpiſe the Lords ordinance &amp; the kingdome of GOD againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, are not to thinke that their paths, whether looſe or ſtraight, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pleaſe the almightie, or will bring them to happines, ſeeing they
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:14627:63"/>leaue the royall and beaten way, wherein the faithfull vſuallie walk vnto ſaluation, and which the Lord himſelfe hath paued and chalked out vnto that intent and purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Wherby as the neceſsitie of the preaching of the word, ſo the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of the myſterie of the Goſpel yet further is made manifeſt vnto vs. The Kings and Princes of this world, haue vnder them their depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and inferious officers in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their iuriſdiction, who deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine cauſes, and gouerne thoſe townes and places which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto their care and charge. Euen ſo Chriſt Ieſus the King of glorie aſcending into heauen, and leading captiuitie captiue,<note place="margin">Pſal. 68.17.</note> gaue gifts vnto men, and placed vnder him ſpirituall Magiſtrates in his church. Indeed the calling of the ciuill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, is not onely ſuch an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb facs="tcp:14627:64"/>of God, as both euerie ſoule ought to be ſubiect vnto,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1</note> and euerie eſtate honour and reuerence as the higheſt and brighteſt glorie vnder heauen:<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.17</note> but ſuch a gift of his vnto the Chriſtian Church,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2 2</note> as that when ſhe enioieth it, ſhe enioieth a crown of comfort and aſsiſtance; when ſhe wanteth it, ſhe wanteth a tower of ſuccour and defence.<note place="margin">Lamen. 2.2</note> Wherefore the eternall wiſedome of God (tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all this while we ſpeak) going about in the booke of the <hi>Prouerbs</hi> to declare, what great gifts ſhe hath in her hand to giue to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and vſeth to beſtowe on her Church, breaketh out into this ſpeach as on a ſodaine, <hi>By me Kings raigne, and Princes decree iuſtice.</hi> In the propheſie of <hi>Eſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.15.</note> the Lord fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telling how bountifullie he would deale with his Church in the laſt daies,<note place="margin">Eſa. 49.23.</note> affirmeth and promiſeth, <hi>that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14627:64"/>Kings ſhall bee nurſing fathers, and Queenes ſhall bee nurſing mothers vnto it.</hi> But beſides the politique gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or cruil Magiſtracie, the Lord hath giuen to his Church the order of the Miniſterie or ſtate eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, that theſe two callings might be as the two eyes of the world, or as the two pearles, of the Chriſtian aſſemblie vppon earth. For as this our Apoſtle teſtifieth vnto the <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians,</hi> our Sauiour aſcending into heauen gaue gifts vnto men, to wit, (as he expoundeth theſe gifts) the callings of Apoſtles, Euangeliſts,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.8.</note> &amp; ſuch other miniſters of the word. The common wealth of Iſrael then is not without her ſpirituall Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, but ſhe partly hath had, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie hath, her gouernours of ſundrie ſortes, as the Apoſtle declareth. Wherein (as before hath been af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed,
<pb facs="tcp:14627:65"/>and after ſhall be made more euident, the excellencie of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of Chriſt Ieſus, and alſo of his miniſterie appeareth; which is oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied about the ſoules of men, and was caſt downe from his treaſure houſe aboue, as a moſt precious Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, euen then when our Sauiour aſcended into heauen. But moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beholde, our heauenlie ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Chriſt, hath ſent foorth his embaſſadors to the <hi>Iewes, Graecians, Scythians, Fgyptians, Morians, Medes. Perſians,</hi> yea (as here is affirmed) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all nations, among which, by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, his name hath been, and is proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Nay, (that which is more) the Lords meſſengers, and publiſhers of his will, ſucceede one another from generation to generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, remaining in ſpight of Sathan and of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, in all places and ages. As for the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14627:65"/>Monarches or Emperours of this world, they vſe to ſend their embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors, not vnto the endes of the worlde or all nations, but to ſome fewe countries, and neere vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Their cuſtome is, to cauſe their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees to be proclaimed only in ſome Cities, or for a fewe daies, not from time to time, and in all the coaſts of the earth. But the Lords Legats thus ſucceeding one another, &amp; preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in many countries, it commeth to paſſe that the kingdom of Chriſt Ieſus, by the courſe of the word, is, hath been, and ſhall be from time to time, glorified, and inlarged in all places.</p>
            <p>For, as further is added in the next argument of the excellencie of the Goſpell, God <hi>hath been beleeued in the world.</hi> Wherein the mighty power and exceeding bountie of the Lord
<pb facs="tcp:14627:66"/>is further manifeſted vnto vs. For preaching is a ſigne of grace offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but faith of grace beſtowed, &amp; of eternall ſaluation. By the gift of faith enemies are made children; beggars, princes; limmes of ſathan, members of Chriſt; fire-brands of hell,<note place="margin">Ephe. 3.6.</note> heires of heauen; old creatures, newe; ſlaues, freemen; captiues, conquerours; yea, more than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours in Chriſt Ieſus. Now, herein the riches of God mercie further appeare, that Chriſt Ieſus is beleeued not in a corner of the world, but throughout the world. <hi>I will make mention</hi> (ſaith the Lord by the Prophet) <hi>of Rahab and Babell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that knowe me: behold the Philistian with him of Tire, and the Aethiopian is borne there.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 87.</note> 
               <hi>And of Sion it ſhall be ſaide, many are borne in her, and he euen the moſt high ſhall eſtabliſh
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14627:66"/>her. The Lord ſhall count, when he wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his people, this man is borne there, Selab.</hi> This aſſemblie of the faithful people of all times, places, and ſorts of perſons, called in the Scripture, not <hi>Rome,</hi> but heauenlie <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> is that Catholicke or vniuerſall Church, which,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.26.</note> whoſoeuer hath not his mother on earth, cannot haue GOD his father in heauen. Part of this Church is alreadie in the higheſt heauens triumphing, parte of it warfaring heere on the earth belowe, parte of it neither in heauen nor on earth as yet, but here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to bee firſt in this world, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condlie in the world to come. The triumphant beleeuers are hidden in the heauens, the pilgrim beleeuers beeing mingled as yellowe corne with chaffe on earth, are ſcant diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, the beleeuers to bee borne
<pb facs="tcp:14627:67"/>haue no being, ſaue in the loynes onely of their forefathers. Faith is a thing not grounded on ſenſe or reaſon, God is inuiſible, Chriſt was a crucified perſon, &amp; is withdrawn from vs as concerning his bodilie preſence, the ſpirite is ſecrete, the world is wide, men are wicked, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants rage: yet GOD hath been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, is beleeued, and ſhall be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued in the world. O depth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable! O glorious myſterie! The vſe hereof is, that euerie one trie whether hee haue that annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that ſeale,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.27. 2. Co. 1.22</note> that earneſt ponie, and that witnes of the ſpirit in him or no: which if he finde, he is to bee more thankfull to God for it, than if he had receiued the greateſt bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite in the world beſides. If he feele not, to ſobbe and ſigh, and pray that God would teſtifie to his ſpirit, that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14627:67"/>he is his father, and beſtow on him this good and heauenlie gift, rather than any earthly bleſsing whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer. But chieflie he is to forſake his euill courſe of life,<note place="margin">Eſa. 1.16.</note> &amp; to walke with God and man in the vprightnes of his heart, which grace going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the peace of hart will vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedlie follow after, ariſing from the ſight of the generalitie and largenes of Gods promiſes,<note place="margin">Heb. 8.10.</note> and the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Gods daylie mercies,<note place="margin">Pſal. 77.</note> and knowledge of the myſterie of chriſt Ieſus here extolled.<note place="margin">Ephe. 3.18.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt point of this myſterie or proofe of the excellencie thereof is, that God hath <hi>been taken vp inglorie.</hi> It was more than a miracle, that the worme before ſpoken of, ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to life, and that the ſecond <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> lying three daies &amp; three nights not aliue, but quite dead in the belly of the earth, did breake the yron
<pb facs="tcp:14627:68"/>bands of the graue, and ſtand vpon the grounde, yea in diuers places preach this Goſpell to his diſciples,<note place="margin">Luk. 24.13.</note> after that he was riſen againe from the dead.<note place="margin">Act. 1.9.</note> But what was it then that his fleſh ſhould mount vppon the clowdes as it were vppon an horſe?<note place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> What was his entrance into the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles not made with hands?<note place="margin">Pſal. 97.7.</note> what was the Angels worſhipping of him, &amp; the fathers enſtalling him in a throne at his right hand? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainlie the glorie of the reſurrection of our Sauiour, ſeemeth not to bee glorious, in regarde of that excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding glorie, into which he is exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his aſcention, farre aboue all powers and principalities, and all creatures whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>Now, here wee may behold the ſonne of GOD leading captiuitie captiue, giuing giftes vnto men, teaching vs as Eagles to mount a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14627:68"/>ſitting by the father as the next perſon, by whom he gouerneth the Churche, prouiding and dreſsing (as it were) many Tabernacles for the elect, and preparing a tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſeate to returne to iudge the earth. Wherefore as his aſcending into heauen, was exceeding glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſo his deſcending thence ſhall yet much more abound in glorie. For then hee ſhall appeare vnto the eyes not of a few, but of all fleſh,<note place="margin">Rom 1.7.</note> not in the contemptible ſhape of a baſe ſeruant, but in the bright and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full maieſtie of the King and Iudge of the whole world.<note place="margin">Act. 1.11</note> At that great day (the day of Doome or Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment knowne onely to GOD, but which cannot be far of from men) theſe writs, to wit, the Sun darkned,<note place="margin">Luk 21.25 Mat. 24.11</note> the moone bloudy, the ſtarres trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, the planets falling down, ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:14627:69"/>goe abroad to ſummon the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the earth, vnto the court where in all cauſes ſhall be ended, &amp; all confuſion of this world ſhall bee corrected. Then, oh where ſhall the amazed people and chayned priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, either faſt their footing, or hide their heads,<note place="margin">Luk. 24.16. 2. Pet. 3.10.</note> when tottering<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and trembling earth, with to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſea, arreſting them before the Tribunal ſeate of the ſonne of God, the clowdie roabe of the reuenging Iudge ſhall terrifie the eyes both of mortall wightes and diuels?<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.16</note> And will not the laſt Trumpet blowne with the blaſt not of a man, but of that Archangel, cauſe the eares of the creatures to tingle and burne, when it ſhall ſound a dolefull and fearefull alarum? Yet againe much more dreadfull muſt needes bee the ſmokie fire,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 1.8</note> which, as breathed out
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14627:69"/>of the noſtrels of the angrie Iudge, ſhal cauſe the Elements to boyle, the townes and Cities of the world to bee turned into aſhes, the faces and ſkinnes of men to be changed as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to tinder. Then, then the graues,<note place="margin">Reu. 20.13 14</note> the waues, the pittes, yea hell it ſelfe alſo, (as the generall iay lours of the whole World) ſhall bring foorth their dead and buried priſoners, to receiue their finall doome at this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne ſeſsions. Thus all ſortes of people arrained at the barre, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by the Angels (as by ſericants or officers) ſhall by them with their hands,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.49</note> and billes or ſwordes as it were, be held and hemmed in on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſide. Here now the ſcrowles of mens conſciences, as euidences,<note place="margin">Reu. 20.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> muſt needes bee vnfoulded, the books ſpoken off in the Reuelation ſhall alſo be vnclaſped, and openlie
<pb facs="tcp:14627:70"/>read. After that all mortall wights haue thus been gathered together, then ſhall a ſeparation bee made of them by the Iudge,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.32.</note> by whom they ſhall bee deuided into two ſorts, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and reprobate, and placed at his two ſides, the right hand &amp; the left. After theſe things, Chriſt firſt ſhall pronounce ſentence on the choſen, ſaying to them;<note place="margin">Mat. 25.34</note> 
               <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my father, poſſeſſe as heires the kingdome prepared for you, before the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the world were layd:</hi> Then pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Elect on thrones,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6, 2.</note> as ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers together with him, to iudge the World, he ſhall pronounce the ſentence of condemnation on the reprobate, ſaying to them, <hi>Departe from mee yee curſed into euerlasting fire,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.41</note> which is prepared for the diuell, and his Angels.</hi> Thus ſhal al men for euer enioy their due reward, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:14627:70"/>life, or the ſecond death.</p>
            <p>And Omortall men, what do ye then meane ſo to loue the world, as if it neuer ſhould haue an end? O vngodly wretches and enemies to all piety in theſe daies, as prophane as <hi>Eſan,</hi> yea more prophane &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly than hee, or <hi>Herod</hi> euer was, will ye needs fulfill the iniquitie of your fathers, graund-fathers, great graund-fathers? Well then, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to worſhip ſtockes, and ſtones, to heare Maſſes, and to creepe to Croſſes: ceaſe not to ſweare dayly, hourely, continually, falſly, vainely, proudly, blaſphemouſly, as yee doo without controlement; braue it, ſport it, feaſt it, loyter it, or (if yee will do ſomething) labour, drudge, run, and ride on the Lords ſabaoth, as your manner is; diſdaine, deſpiſe, curſe, murmur and rebell againſt
<pb facs="tcp:14627:71"/>your magiſtrates, teachers, parents, maſters, ſuperiours; imb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue your hearts, hands, tongues, and weapons in innocent bloud, ſparing neither bodies, good names, nor ſoules of old fathers, men, women, little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; bath your ſelues in daintines, wantonnes, idlenes, drunkennes, hunting, hanking, carding, dicing, and all kindes of paſtime: vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin your houſes with the bones of your poore tenaunts, neighbours, brethren, kinſfolke; lay the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of them on their carcaſes, hang the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> about with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ir skinnes, yea, and with the skinnes of their wiues and children (a goodly kinde of tapiſterie) plaiſter them with their entralles, paint them with their bloud, waſh them euery day with their teares. To conclude (O croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and peruerſe generation) tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14627:71"/>vnder your feete the precious bloud of GOD, manifeſted in the fleſh, iuſtified in the ſpirit, ſeene of Angels, preached vnto the Nations, beleeued in the world, receiued vp in glorie: but knowe, that for all theſe things hee ſhall come vnto iudgement.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe as concerning thoſe, vnto whom the myſterie of godlines ſeemeth without doubte very great, vnto whom Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is the only treaſure in the world, who indeauour with vprightnes to obey his lawes and word, there is no cauſe why they ſhould quake to thinke on his returne to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but rather great reaſon, why they ſhould pray. <hi>come Lord Ieſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 22.20</note> 
               <hi>come quickly.</hi> For ſeeing he hath ſhed his precious bloud for you, will he, or can he pronounce a bloudie ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb facs="tcp:14627:72"/>againſt you? Is it credible that the head, which laide it ſelfe down for the body, wil adiudge his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers vnto torment? Should the ſpouſe, bought with a price aboue gold orſiluer, and loued more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely than any treaſure, be afraid to ſee hir moſt amiable husbands face<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Is there no more fauour or tender affection in an elder brother, than to deale with boanes of his boanes, &amp; fleſh of his fleſh rigorouſly? Will a gracious King rather cruelly ſlay his ſubiects, crauing pardon, than ſhew his mercy in ſauing and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancing them to honour? Was the Sonne of GOD ſometimes ſo carefull a ſhepheard, as to ſeeke that which was loſt, and will hee not preſerue that which he hath found? To conclude therefore, he was firſt manifeſted in the fleſh, and after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14627:72"/>vp in glorie, that whoſoeuer beleeue in him, ſhould not periſh, but haue life euerlaſting, and bee made Kings and Prieſts with him for euer, obeying the Lorde with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſiſtance, ſeruing him without corruption, gouerned by him as by a glorified prieſt and Prophet, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch temporall meanes as now are in vſe, yea as are very neceſſarie and profitable for the faithful, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring heere on earth. But at that time ſhall tongues ceaſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie be aboliſhed,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.1.</note> and Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſhall deliuer vp to his Father the temporall part of his rule,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.24.</note> which now he exerciſeth not onely in the world, but in the Church. For now he inſtructeth his people by the Miniſterie of men, then they ſhall not need any ſuch teachers, now he
<pb facs="tcp:14627:73"/>feedeth them by outward Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but then hee ſhall bee the onely Lambe and bread of life; now he fighteth againſt or reſiſteth ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, but then he ſhall ſo breake his head, that hee ſhall fully conquer him.</p>
            <p>Finally, now hee is to come to iudge the world, and to raiſe vp the dead, but hereafter hee ſhall ceaſe from theſe workes. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſtill he ſhall remaine the light, glorie,<note place="margin">Reuel. 21.22, 23.</note> and flower of the temple, gouerning both Angels and men immediatlie by his perſon and his ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Thus Elect creatures ſhall (as members) be vnited vnto God, and God ſhall bee all in all, euen the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to whom with the Sonne, and the Spirite, three perſons and one
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14627:73"/>heauenly Maieſtie, bee all praiſe and glory both now and euer, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Amen.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 11.33.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>O ther deepenes of the riches both of the wiſdome and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, how vnſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able are his iudgements, and his waies past finding out.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14627:74"/>
            <head>A requeſt to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>ſtian Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, I have herein, onelie drawne the picture of Chriſt Ieſus after a rude and ſimple manner, as it were with a peece of chalke, or with a coale. But if thou ſhalt ſeeke him in the Miniſterie or preaching of the worde, and the Lord withall ſhall cauſe the day ſtarre to ariſe in thine heart, thou ſhalt ſee him ſo liuelie painted before thine eyes, &amp; beholde him ſo clere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie as in a Cristall glaſſe, that thou ſhalt be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into his image from glorie to glorie, not continuing in ſinne, becauſe grace dooth abound. (for thou hast not ſo learned Christ) but putting off the olde man,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note> and <hi>putting on the new man, which is created according to God in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and true holines.</hi> No more vnto thee (whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer thou art which louest Christ Ieſus) at this preſent, ſaue onely thus much, let him be the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hine heart. <hi>Manie ſay, oh if one would cauſe vs to ſee good: oh Iehoua lift thou vp the light of thy countenance on vs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 4.7.</note> Then ſhalt thou put greater ioye into our heart, than of the time wherein their corne and new wine have beene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed. Farewell.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
